原创翻译  双语字幕
仅供学习 禁止用于任何商业盈利行为
更多影视更新
请登陆www.ZiMuZu.tv
翻译：麦田守望者  showeryhe  盐湖凉开水
翻译：cjr200  回风舞雪兮  杨一勾
翻译：酱油  Cath233
校对：持久  阿鸟
后期：8T     总监：持久  somehacker
让我们陷入困境的不是无知
而是看似正确的谬误论断
马克·吐温
弗兰克  家人都好吗
Hiya, Frank. How are the wife and kids?
我觉得国库券和公共事业股票
You know, for you, I'm considering treasury bonds
比较适合你  抽烟吗
and utility stocks. Smoke?
在七十年代末  银行业
In the late '70s, banking wasn't a job
可赚不了大钱
you went into to make large sums of money.
就是他妈的小打小闹
It was a fucking snooze.
纽约大都会赢了吗
How about those Mets?
充斥着废柴  比如卖保险的
Filled with losers. Like selling insurance or
或者会计师
accounting.
如果说银行业无聊的话
And if banking was boring,
那银行的债券部门简直就让人昏昏欲睡
then the bond department at the bank was straight-up comatose.
我们都知道债券是怎么回事
We all know about bonds.
在你那还流着鼻涕的孩子满十五岁时给他
You give them to your snot-nosed kid when he turns 15.
也许等他到了三十岁能赚个一百块
Maybe when he's 30 he makes a hundred bucks.
无聊
Boring.
直到所罗门兄弟银行的
That is, until Lewis Ranieri came on the scene
路易斯·拉涅利出现
at Salomon Brothers.
你也许不知道他是谁  但他对你生活的改变
You might not know who he is, but he changed your life
比迈克尔·乔丹  iPod和油管的总和都多
more than Michael Jordan, the iPod and YouTube put together.
好了先生们  我们来赚钱吧
All right, gentlemen! Let's get some money in here!
我们来赚钱吧  你们说怎么样
Let's make some money! What do you say?
路易斯还没有意识到
You see, Lewis didn't know it yet,
但他只用了一个简单的点子
but he had already changed banking forever
就永远改变了银行业
with one simple idea.
住房抵押贷款支持证券
The mortgage-backed security.
或者弄成品牌叫MBS
Or private-label MBS.
你们都有普通的住房抵押贷款
You've got your average person's mortgage.
固定利率  三十年期
Fixed rate, 30 years.
风险小  回报低  对吧
Boring, safe, small payoff, right? But,
但当你把成千上万的贷款绑在一起
when you have thousands of them all bundled together,
突然间投资收益上升了但风险依然很小
suddenly the yield goes up but the risk is still small because,
因为它们是住房抵押贷款
well, they're mortgages!
谁会不还住房抵押贷款呢
And who the hell doesn't pay their mortgage?
这种债券的信用评级是多少
What exactly is the credit rating on this bond?
先生们  这种债券是AAA级的
This bond, gentlemen, is AAA-rated.
这正是密歇根州立
This is exactly what the
养老基金在寻找的投资
Michigan state pension fund has been looking for.
我要买两千万
I'll buy $20 million.
拜托  胆子大一点
Oh, come on, live a little.
两千五百万
$25 million.
钱源源不断地来了
The money came raining down,
史上第一次
and for the first time,
银行家们从乡村俱乐部到了脱衣舞俱乐部
the banker went from the country club to the strip club.
很快  股票和储蓄变得无足轻重
Pretty soon, stocks and savings were almost inconsequential.
他们一年里创造了五百亿  一千亿...
They were doing $50, $100, $200 billion
两千亿的抵押债券和其他形式的债券
in mortgage bonds and dozens of other securities a year.
美国人并没有注意到第一行业
And America barely noticed as its number one industry
变成了无聊的银行业
became boring old banking.
后来有一天  大概三十年后  2008年
And then one day, almost 30 years later, in 2008,
泡沫破裂  经济崩盘
it all came crashing down.
三月  贝尔斯登公司严重亏损
March. Bear Stearns was in a death spiral
联邦政府促成了它的被收购
and the Fed brokered its sale.
这被称作
It's been
当代最严重的金融危机
called the worst financial crisis in modern times.
毫无疑问是这个国家
Certainly the largest
几十年以来最大的金融危机
financial disaster in decades in this country,
也许是美国经济一个时代的终结
and perhaps the end of an era in American business.
到头来  路易斯·拉涅利的住房抵押贷款支持证券
In the end, Lewis Ranieri's mortgage-backed security
突变成了使世界经济
mutated into a monstrosity
崩溃的怪兽
that collapsed the whole world economy.
而且没有任何专家
And none of the experts or
领袖或发言人事先知道这一点
leaders or talking heads had a clue it was coming.
我猜你们中的大部分还一无所知
I'm guessing most of you still don't really know what happened.
为了不显得太蠢
Yeah, you got a soundbite you
你会重复电视采访的说法  但得了吧
repeat so you don't sound dumb, but come on.
我们的财政机构是强大的
Our financial institutions are strong.
但还是有人预测出了它的来临
But there were some who saw it coming.
当整个世界都在狂欢时
While the whole world was having a big old party,
一些局外人和怪人看到了别人看不见的
a few outsiders and weirdos saw what no one else could.
不是我  我不是怪人  我很酷
Not me. I'm not a weirdo. I'm pretty fucking cool.
但我们一会儿会再见面的
But we'll meet again later.
这些局外人看到了经济中心的巨大谎言
These outsiders saw the giant lie at the heart of the economy.
他们是通过做其他二货
And they saw it by doing something
没有想到的事情看出来的
the rest of the suckers never thought to do.
他们仔细研究过
They looked.
大空头
在二十世纪三十年代
During the 1930s,
全国范围的房屋市场蒸发了
the housing market collapsed nationwide
近80%的财富
by roughly 80%.
半数的住房抵押贷款都违约了
I mean, half of all mortgage debt was in default.
我是说  这有
And, I mean, there were very
非常具体的标志  非常容易识别
specific identifiers, extremely recognizable.
比如说
I mean, for instance,
狂热的标志之一是
one of the hallmarks of mania
衍生品的复杂性
is the rapid rise
和欺诈比例的快速增长
in complexity and the rates of fraud.
你知道它们在持续上升吗
And did you know that they're going up?
我总是在
I've always been
独自一人时感觉更舒适
more comfortable alone.
我觉得可能是因为我的玻璃眼睛
I believe maybe it's because of my glass eye.
我在童年疾病中失去了一只眼睛
I lost the eye in a childhood illness.
它使我和他人隔绝
It separates me from people.
你知道它们在
And did you know that they are going
持续上升吗
up?
自从二十世纪三十年代以来的最高的欺诈率
The highest fraud rates since the 1930s.
没事的  没事的
Hey, hey, it's okay. It's okay.
不  我不知道
No, I didn't know that.
在1933年  大萧条的第四年
In 1933, the fourth year of the Great Depression.
我们洗一洗再把它装回去
Let's wash it off and put it back in.
你打得很好  儿子
You were playing so great, son.
教练都这么说了
I even heard the coach say it.
我们能回家吗
Can we just go home?
大多数的社交活动对我和其他人而言都是尴尬的
Most social interactions are awkward for me and for the person.
哪怕当我试着称赞某人
Even when I try to compliment someone,
都事与愿违
it comes out wrong.
你发型不错  自己剪的吗
You have a very nice haircut. Did you do it yourself?
什么
What?
不  不  我
No. No, I...
抱歉  我只是
I'm sorry. I'm just...
我话太多了
I'm going on and on.
我妻子跟我说我需要多分享
My wife told me I need to share more.
-看起来挺健康的  -是啊
- That seems healthy. - Yeah.
我应聘成功了吗
So do I get the job?
我真的觉得我可以帮到你的基金
I really think I could help your fund.
是的
Yeah.
当然  你去把
Yeah, sure. Go on.
-你叫...  -David  太好了
- You're... - David. Great.
我去找张办公桌
I guess I'll go find a desk.
你有什么想让我开始做的吗
Is there anything you want me to work on for start...
好
Yeah.
你可以待会儿再告诉我  我再过来
You could let me know later. I could come back.
你觉得2001年技术泡沫破裂
Did you think it was strange when, um,
而作为世界技术之都的
the tech bubble burst in 2001
圣何塞房市高涨
and the housing market in San Jose,
同时发生
the tech capital of the world,
奇怪吗
went up?
难道不奇怪吗
Wasn't that strange?
不
No.
不  因为是住房  住房很稳固
No, it's housing. Housing is always stable.
低风险  稳定的
Low risk. It's solid.
是这么回事
That's the idea, yeah.
我要你给我找出
I want you to get me
卖的最好的前二十位的抵押债券
the top 20 selling mortgage bonds.
你是想知道这些债券都是什么吗
So you want to know what the top 20 selling mortgage bonds are?
不  我要知道每种债券都是哪些房贷支持的
No, no, no, I want to know what mortgages are in each one.
那些房贷不是由...
Okay, aren't those mortgages made up of...
等等  那些债券不是由
Wait, aren't those bonds made up
成千上万的房贷组成吗
of thousands and thousands of mortgages?
是的
Yeah.
马上去  柏利博士
Right away, Dr. Burry.
我是个好人
I am a nice guy all day long.
随便问问谁  我和人相处融洽
Ask anyone, I'm a pleasure to work with.
但一旦我儿子搞砸了  我
But the second my son screws up, I am...
冲他吼得就像我父亲吼我一样
...yelling at him just like my dad did to me.
我听见从嘴里出来的话
I hear the words that are coming out of my mouth and...
抱歉我迟到了  打不到车
Sorry I'm late! No cabs.
听听这个
So, get this.
我昨天见了一位零售银行家
I met with this retail banker yesterday.
我本来应该让他投资一个基金的
I'm supposed to be getting him to invest in a fund,
但取而代之的是
but instead
我开始盘问他透支的罚金
I start grilling him about overdraft penalties
以及他的银行是如何让顾客写了
and how his bank will let a customer write 10-12 checks
十到十二张支票才告诉他们已透支的
before they tell them they're overdrawn.
这个变态
And this creep is making
通过这种方式挣了上百万
billions off screwing over people this way.
我越来越生气
And I'm getting madder and madder.
我看着他的脸对他说
And I ask him, I look him in the face and I say,
"你明知在剥削工薪阶层
"How can you sleep at night
晚上还怎么睡得着"
knowing that you are ripping off working people?"
你们知道他怎么做的吗  他走了
And you know what he did? He left.
他就那么走了  什么都没说
He just walks out of the lunch, doesn't say a word.
他妈的这算什么
What the fuck is that?
那种情形下是谁搞砸了  是我吗
Who's fucked up in that scenario? Am I?
还是把我晾在那里的那个混蛋
Or is this douchebag, who leaves me hanging?
是他搞砸了吗
Is he the fucked up one?
我们已经谈论过很多次了
We have talked about this numerous times.
你不能迟到还劫持整个互助会
You can't come in late and hijack the entire session.
什么意思  我并没有劫持互助会
What do you mean? I didn't hijack the meeting.
我劫持了互助会吗
Did I hijack the session?
是的
Yeah.
你是做什么的
What do you do?
我做期货的
I'm in commodities.
祝你好运
Good luck with that.
马克  我知道你损失了很多
Mark, I know you suffered a terrible loss.
也许你想谈谈这个
Maybe you want to talk about that.
我不想谈
I don't talk about that.
稍等
Hold on.
等一下
Hold on...
该死  这个我必须得接  抱歉
Shit, I have to take this. Sorry. Sorry.
不  我不管  波特
No... I don't care, Porter.
这家伙的生意是建立在剥削他人之上
This guy's whole business is built on ripping people off.
这样能维持多久
How long can that last?
各位再见
Bye, everybody!
九十五
95...
那是三十天后  六十天后
That's 30 days late... Sixty days late...
他们付款及时...
They pay on time...
这些信贷评分...
These FICO scores...
晚了  他们被发现...
Late. And they caught up on their payments...
又晚了三十天付款...
Another 30 days late...
客户终身价值  95  90  他们被发现...
LTV, 95... LTV, 90... They caught up on their payments...
晚了六十天付款  天哪
Sixty days late? Jesus!
客户终身价值  110  从没见过这样的
LTV, 110? I've never heard of that!
晚了三十天  利率调整
Thirty days late, rate adjusts...
07年调整了
In '07 rate adjusts...
06年调整了
In '06 rate adjusts...
95  90  天哪
95... 90... Jesus!
他一整天都没离开过
He hasn't moved all day.
他每隔几天就会这样
He does this every few days.
他雇了我之后就没跟我说过话
He hasn't spoken to me since he hired me.
也许客户终身价值在...  高风险
Maybe the LTV's at... High-risk,
只有利率  我从没听过那个抵押历史
interest-only... I never heard of that mortgage history,
我从没听过  怎么可能
I never heard of that... How?
迈克尔  你好吗
Michael, how are you, guy?
劳伦斯  我发现了些很有趣的事
Lawrence, I found something really interesting.
很好  迈克尔  每次你发现有趣的事
Great, Michael. Whenever you find something interesting,
我们都赚钱了
we all tend to make money.
你在估值哪只股票
What stock are you valuing?
不  不是股票
No, no, no, no. No stocks.
我想要做空房地产市场
I want to short the housing market.
是吗  房地产市场可是稳如磐石啊
Really? But the housing market is rock solid.
格林斯潘刚刚才说
Greenspan just said
泡沫是区域性的  违约是少见的
bubbles are regional, defaults are rare.
告诉他们我一会儿就来
Tell them I'll be there in a minute.
-再说一遍  -听着
- Say again? - Look, look...
格林斯潘是错误的
Greenspan's wrong.
我觉得你不是故意这样的  但有时你听起来
I don't think you mean to do this, but sometimes you sound very
相当轻蔑  满是优越感
dismissive and superior.
这是事实  格林斯潘是错的
It's a fact. Greenspan's wrong.
我不知道你还想让我说什么
I don't know how else you want me to say...
迈克尔
Look, Michael.
大都会资本四年前在你
Metro Capital backed you four years ago
还只是一名医生  只有一个
when you were a doctor with a
小网站和一些遗产的时候支持了你
dinky webpage and some inheritance money.
我们都做得很好
We've all done very well.
你为什么不专注于股票呢
Why don't you just stick with stocks?
你了解我  我...
Look. You know me. I, I, I...
我会寻找一切投资价值
I look for value wherever it can be found.
事实是
And the fact is
那些住房抵押贷款支持证券充满了
that these mortgage-backed securities are filled
极度危险的可调利率次级贷款
with extremely risky subprime adjustable-rate loans.
等大多数浮动利率
And when the majority of the adjustable rates
在07年开始执行时
kick in, in '07,
他们就会开始下跌
they will begin to fail.
如果下跌超过15%  整个债券就一文不值了
And if they fail above 15%, the whole bond is worthless.
迈克尔  休息一下
Michael, just take a beat.
我们晚点再谈这个  好吗
We'll talk about this later, okay?
劳伦斯  请不要敷衍我  听着
Lawrence, please, don't patronize me. Listen...
住房抵押贷款支持证券
Mortgage-backed securities.
它
It, it, it...
次级贷款  打包在一起
Subprime loans. Tranches.
很难懂的概念  对吗
It's pretty confusing, right?
让你觉得厌烦  或者愚蠢吗
Does it make you feel bored? Or stupid?
就应该这样
Well, it's supposed to.
华尔街喜欢用复杂的概念
Wall Street loves to use confusing terms
让你觉得只有他们才能做那些事情
to make you think only they can do what they do.
或者更好的是
Or, even better,
让你远离他们
for you to just leave them the fuck alone.
所以用玛格特·罗比的泡泡浴解释一下
So here's Margot Robbie in a bubble bath to explain.
通常来说  路易斯·拉涅利的抵押债券
Basically, Lewis Ranieri's mortgage bonds
对于大银行来说利润丰厚
were amazingly profitable for the big banks.
他们通过卖这些债券所收取的
They made billions and billions on their 2% fee
2%的手续费赚取了亿万财富
they got for selling each of these bonds.
但接着抵押住房资源开始枯竭
But then they started running out of mortgages to put in them.
毕竟只有那么多的房屋
After all, there are only so many homes
只有那么多有能力买它们的人
and so many people with good enough jobs to buy them, right?
于是银行开始用更有风险的
So the banks started filling these bonds
房贷来支持这些债券
with riskier and riskier mortgages.
谢谢你  本特
Thank you, Benter.
那样的话他们就能继续盈利了  对把
That way they can keep that profit machine churning, right?
对了  这些高风险房贷叫次级贷款
By the way, these risky mortgages are called subprime.
所以每当你听见次级贷款
So whenever you hear "Subprime", think
就意味着狗屎
"Shit".
我们的朋友迈克尔·柏利发现了这些抵押债券
Our friend Michael Burry found out that these mortgage bonds
本应该65%都是AAA级组成
that were supposedly 65% AAA
实际上大部分都是狗屎
were actually just mostly full of shit.
所以他现在要做空这些债券
So now he's going to "Short" the bonds.
意思是说打赌它要完蛋
Which means to "Bet against".
明白了吗
Got it?
很好
Good.
现在滚蛋吧
Now fuck off.
其他人发现这个投资机会
It's only a matter of time
只是时间问题
before someone else sees this investment.
我们现在就需要行动
We have to act now!
你怎么知道债券没有价值
How do you know the bonds are worthless?
他们不是都是上千页的
Aren't they filled with fucking thousands
房贷支持的吗
of pages of mortgages?
我读过它们了
I read them.
-你读过了  -我读过了  是的
- You read them? - I read... Yes.
没人会读它们
No one reads them. Only
只有整理它们的律师才会读它们
the lawyers who put them together read them.
听着  我觉得他们都不知道自己创造了什么
Look, I don't think that they even know what they've made.
房地产市场是由这些糟糕的
The housing market is propped up on these
房贷撑起来的
bad loans, and I'm...
这是颗定时炸弹  我想做空它
It's a time bomb, and I want to short it.
用什么金融工具呢  迈克尔
Through what instrument, Michael?
抵押债券没有保险合同或者期权
There are no insurance contracts or options for mortgage bonds.
债券太稳固了
The bonds are too stable.
劳伦斯
Lawrence...
我准备这么做  我要找家银行
This is what I'm gonna do. I am gonna get a bank
给我做一个
to make me one.
然后
And then
我会买下来
I'm gonna buy it.
我不想做那种生意
I don't want that kind of business.
要赚钱有道  那是不义之财
Money is not money. That's bad money.
拜托
Hey! Excuse me!
我问你  有哪家公司对待顾客
Let me ask you this. What company treats its customers
那么糟糕还能成功的
that shittily and succeeds?
好吧  高盛  有道理
Fine. Okay, Goldman. You're right.
马克·鲍姆在工作中
Mark Baum had built his
坚信没有证据就不能假设任何人
career on never assuming anyone or any company
或任何公司是合法的
was legit without proving it.
他小时候在正统犹太小学
When he was a kid he excelled
学习《塔木德经》异常出色  随便了
at studying the Talmud in Yeshiva. Whatever.
但有一天拉比告诉了他妈妈原因
But one day his rabbi told his mom why.
保罗这孩子不错
Paul is a fine boy,
而马克《律法书》
and Mark is an excellent student
和《塔木德经》都学得很好
of the Torah and the Talmud.
那有什么问题吗  拉比
Then what's the problem, rabbi?
关键在于马克那么努力学习的原因
It's the reason Mark is studying so hard.
他想找出真主话语里前后不一致的地方
He's looking for inconsistencies in the word of God!
那他找到了吗
So has he found any?
后来鲍姆在华尔街设立了自己的基金
Later, Baum started his own fund on Wall Street.
他对牛粪反应灵敏
He had an amazing nose for bullshit.
他不担心让别人知道
And he wasn't afraid to let anyone know when and where
何时何地牛就要拉屎了
the bull had gone number two.
但后来马克遇上了悲剧
But then a tragedy happened to Mark,
使他的世界观变得一片黑暗
and it turned his world view dark
相信整个系统都谎话连篇
and ready to believe the whole system was a lie.
稍等
Hold on.
是辛西娅
It's Cynthia.
我二十分钟内到办公室
I'll be in the office in 20 minutes.
亲爱的
Hi, honey.
心理医生打电话来  你又那样了
The therapist called. You did it again.
打不到车  你说我该怎么办
There were no cabs. What was I supposed to do?
我担心你  马克
I worry about you, Mark.
至少我去了
At least I went.
你这样奔来跑去好像要
You're running around like you have to right
-拯救世界  -好吧
- every wrong in the world. - Okay.
你总是很愤怒
You're so angry.
好吧  不如这样
Fine. You know what?
我是个刻薄鬼  而且我生气了
I'm a mean guy and I'm pissed off.
但马上有场暴屎雨要来袭  亲爱的
But it is a shit storm out here, sweetie.
你根本不知道人们都在搞什么鬼
You have no idea the kind of crap people are pulling.
而他们都像
And everyone's walking
恩雅的MV里那样走来走去
around like they're in a goddamn Enya video.
他们都要完蛋了
They're all getting screwed, you know.
你知道他们在乎什么吗
You know what they care about?
他们只关心球赛
They care about the ballgame.
或者哪个女演员进了戒毒所
Or they care about what actress just went into rehab.
我觉得你该试试药物治疗
I think you should try medication.
不行  我们已经达成一致了
No, no. We agreed.
那会影响工作
If it interfered with work.
你讨厌华尔街  或许是时候退出了
You hate Wall Street. Maybe it's time to quit.
-我爱我的工作  -你讨厌你的工作
- I love my job. - You hate your job.
我爱我的工作
I love my job.
你真可怜
You're miserable.
我爱我的工作
I love my job.
我爱我的工作  亲爱的
I love my job, honey.
马克
Mark...
我每天都为发生的事情悲伤
I am sad every day about what happened.
我知道你也是这种感觉
I know you must feel the same,
只是从没表现出来
but you never show it.
我知道你跟哥哥关系有多好
I know how close you were to your brother.
保罗
Paul.
你去哪儿了  保罗
Where'd you go, Paul?
保罗
Paul!
我每天都以为你会跟我谈  可你从没有
Every day I think you're gonna talk about it, but you never do.
你能否至少考虑一下做点改变
Will you at least think about the idea of making a change?
好吧  亲爱的  我会考虑的
Fine. Fine. Honey, you know what? I will consider it.
但说实话  辛西娅
But, honestly, Cynthia.
我没事  真的
I'm okay. I really am.
不行
No, no.
这是我的出租车
My cab. That's my cab.
我的出租车
That's my cab. That is my cab.
-白痴  滚蛋  -滚蛋
- Schmuck. Fuck you. - Fuck you.
-滚蛋  -滚蛋
- Fuck you. - Fuck you.
我待会儿打给你
I'll call you later.
我想买抵押债券的掉期
I want to buy swaps on mortgage bonds.
一种信用违约的掉期  如果相关债券违约
A credit default swap that will pay off
我将得到收益
if the underlying bond fails.
你想反赌房地产市场吗
You want to bet against the housing market?
-是的  -为什么
- Yes. - Why?
只有当上百万美国人
Those bonds only fail
都不偿付房贷  这些债券才会违约
if millions of Americans don't pay their mortgages.
这在历史上还从未发生
That's never happened in history.
希望你不要介意  柏利博士
If you'll excuse me, Dr. Burry,
这看上去是笔愚蠢的投资
it seems like a foolish investment.
基于流行文化中
Well, based on prevailing sentiment
对市场和银行的主流态度
of the market and banks in popular culture,
没错  这确实是笔愚蠢的投资
yes, it's a foolish investment.
但  所有人都错了
But, uh... everyone's wrong.
这说法不错
That's a good one.
这可是华尔街  柏利博士
This is Wall Street, Dr. Burry.
如果你要送钱上门  我们自然会接受
If you offer us free money, we are going to take it.
我只担心一点  等债券崩盘的时候
My one concern is that when the bonds fail,
我需要确定能得到款项支付
uh, I want to be certain, um, of payment
以防贵银行没有偿付能力
um, in case of solvency issues with your bank.
抱歉  你是说真的吗
I'm sorry, are you for real?
你打算反赌房地产市场
You wanna bet against the housing market
而且担心我们不会给你钱
and you're worried we won't pay you?
没错  我是这个意思
Yes, that's correct.
...除非市场崩溃
... unless the market crashes.
房地产市场不可能崩盘
The market on housing's never gonna crash
因为它现在非常坚挺
because it's so solid right now.
我是说  谁会不还房贷呢
I mean, who doesn't pay their mortgages?
柏利博士  我们可以设计一套
Dr. Burry, we could work out
即时支付的结构
a pay-as-we-go structure
只要债券跌价立即支付
that would pay out if the bonds fail.
但如果抵押债券涨价
But it would also apply to your
那么你也要付我们钱
payments if the value of the mortgage bond goes up.
你要按月支付我们溢价
You'd have to pay us monthly premiums.
可以接受吗  柏利博士
Is that acceptable, Dr. Burry?
可以  好的
Yes. Yes.
这里有六家住房抵押贷款支持证券的
Um, I have prospectuses on six
募股文件  我想做空它们
mortgage-backed securities I want to short.
这些房贷大部分...
Majority of the mortgages...
我看我们根本不可能亏钱
I don't see us losing any money on these at all.
柏利博士  这样就可以了
Dr. Burry, these should be fine.
我们打算卖你五百万美元
Yeah. We're prepared to sell you $5 million
这些抵押债券的信用违约掉期
in credit default swaps on these mortgage bonds.
能卖一个亿吗
Can we make it $100 million?
当然可以卖一个亿
Uh, absolutely, we can make it $100 million.
我们会再联系  送一些文件过来
We'll be in touch, send some paperwork over.
我喜欢这些杯子
I like these cups.
我能给我儿子拿一个吗
Can I take one for my son?
拿吧  当然
Have... Yes. Yes.
谢谢
Thank you.
拿两个吧
Have two.
我要我的钱
德意志银行
可以来两亿吗
Is there any way to do $200 million?
我们可以  但你确定吗
I mean, we can. But are you sure?
当然  当然  可以的
Absolutely. Absolutely, we can do that.
美国国家金融服务公司
银行&房贷
美国银行
坎迪·西尔韦拉
4H社区服务于特洛克西区的负责人
我们做各种项目  我们搞园艺
We do different projects. We do gardening.
我们打算反赌的债券
The bonds I'd like to bet against.
贝尔斯登集团
在大荧幕上看到自己也不赖
It's not bad seeing yourself on the big screen.
感觉很棒
It's very cool.
我点了1.3斤丁骨牛排
I ordered the 24-ounce T-bone,
这是我的选择
which was choice.
-我追求体积  -没错
- I went for volume... - Yeah.
不要求质量
... rather than prime.
我追求次级贷款  要点在于
I went for subprime, and the gist was...
我们想你
兰德尔·多姆怎么了
Hey, Randall! What's with the Dom?
三个月没发奖金了
Bonuses aren't for three months.
我们刚卖了两亿
We just sold $200 million
抵押债券的信用掉期
in credit swaps for mortgage bonds.
加州来的一个基金经理
Some fund manager from California.
太他妈疯狂了  是吧
It's fucking crazy, right?
赚钱的新路子  道格
A whole new way to make money, Doug.
慢着  我都不知有抵押贷款的掉期
Wait, wait. I didn't know there were swaps on mortgages.
现在有了  我们替他设计的
There are now. We made it for him.
他肯定是抗抑郁药吃多了之类的
He must have gone off his Zoloft or something.
我也不知道
I don't know.
-一起来  不来吗  -稍等
- Want to join? No? - Just a second.
杰瑞德
Hey, Jared.
你听说兰德尔跟一个基金经理
Did you hear about the deal that Randall just did
刚做的交易吗
with some fund manager?
兰德尔吗  胡扯
Randall? Bullshit.
他是个小角色  我敢肯定这交易很差劲
He's a foot soldier. I'm sure it's a shit deal.
杰瑞德·温尼特
是真的
No, it's for real.
我说了待会儿再见
I told you we'd meet later.
可惜是在这样一个地方
Unfortunately, it's in a place like this
我根本不想来的地方
which I would never be.
我再也不想下班后跟这些白痴出来玩了
I never hung out with these idiots after work, ever.
我也有过入时的朋友
I had fashion friends.
似乎这家伙想买两亿
Apparently, this guy wanted $200 mil
信用违约掉期
in credit default swaps.
兰德尔达成了这笔交易
Randall made the sale.
你能相信吗
Can you believe it?
有人做空了两亿的抵押债券
Somebody shorted $200 mil on mortgage bonds?
还只是跟德意志银行
That was just with Deutsche.
据说他找了城里一半的投行
Word is he hit half the town.
总共多少
How much in total?
十三亿
$1.3 billion.
什么
What?
这差不多是赛恩全部的流动资金了
That's pretty much all of Scion's liquidity.
迈克尔  这下麻烦大了
Michael, this is highly distressing.
劳伦斯  这绝不是
Lawrence, that is not
我们全部的流动资金
all of our liquidity.
而且我不确定
And I'm not certain
你真的理解这笔交易
that you really understand this trade.
这是必然事件
This is a certainty.
我自以为是你的导师
Mike, I consider myself a mentor to you.
但我们公司
But our company is not
不喜欢这笔投资  我说清楚了吗
comfortable with this investment. Am I being clear?
劳伦斯  对于投资策略
Lawrence, I have full autonomy
我有完全的自主权
when it comes to investment strategy.
你可以看我们的合约
You can read our agreement.
别跟我提最开始的合约  迈克尔
Do not throw our inception agreement in my face, Michael.
我们当时以为
We had an underlying understanding
你不会像疯子那样做事
you wouldn't act like a goddamn crazy man.
这不是发疯
This is not crazy.
完全合乎逻辑
It's all very logical.
抵押贷款跌价前我们都得支付
So, now we pay up premiums on these swaps
这些房地产市场掉期的溢价
against the housing market until the mortgages fail?
换句话说  在永远不会发生的事情
In other words, we lose millions
发生之前我们就要损失上百万
until something that's never happened before happens?
房利美[联邦住房抵押协会]
我是自己命运的主人
自己灵魂的上尉
没错
That's correct.
《全球市场中的知识产权》
《股市逻辑》
《房地产估值》
亚当·斯密
信用违约掉期的溢价
信用违约掉期
无主题
我想要利润  而不是溢价
你疯了吗
房地产创新高
撤回资金
马克·鲍姆
Hello, Mark Baum.
凯西  被你逮到了
Oh, hey, Kathy, you busted me.
我下午有私事
I had a personal thing this afternoon.
我又不是你的保姆
I'm not your babysitter.
只要FrontPoint能帮摩根斯坦利赚钱就行
If FrontPoint makes money for Morgan Stanley, I'm happy.
好  你是怀孕了吗
Okay. Hey, did I hear you're expecting?
我们希望能怀孕
We're expecting to be expecting.
体外受精要把家底都掏空了
IVF's are cleaning us out
但我们还是很乐观
but we're staying positive...
振奋人心啊
That's exciting!
蛋蛋有肿块  我去做了扫描
... lump on my ball. And I go in for a scan.
结果发现我有个大家伙  叫做附睾
Turns out that I have a very large thing called an epididymis.
就在蛋蛋旁边
Which is a thing that goes around the ball
类似下层有个小囊
and is like a sac underneath.
红肿的附睾
我有一枚格外
I have an extremely
-明显的附睾  -有意思
- pronounced epididymis. - I'm riveted...
我很有兴趣  有照片吗
I'm riveted by this. Do you have any pictures?
特别大  就像睾丸上面又长了一枚睾丸
It's almost as large as another testicle unto itself.
听我说  辛西娅
So get this. Cynthia...
伙计们  辛西娅希望我辞职
Guys. Cynthia wants me to quit
去佛蒙特州开家庭旅馆
and open a B&B in Vermont.
听起来不错
That sounds great. I'd
我很乐意见到马克·鲍姆铺床做早餐
love to see Mark Baum run a bed and breakfast.
比如  "这是你的钢切燕麦  混蛋"
Like, "Here's your steel-cut oatmeal, asshole."
马克拒绝向带着支票簿的人表示尊重
Mark refused to kiss the ring of the people with the checkbooks,
所以他只能在摩根斯坦利的势力下
so he had to set up his fund under
建立自己的基金
Morgan Stanley's umbrella.
他的小团队反映出他对这个系统的不信任
His small team reflected his distrust of the system.
你们这些家伙太恶心了
You guys are sick. You're sick.
她说这份工作害我不开心
She says this job is making me unhappy.
但你不开心的时候就很开心
But you're happy when you're unhappy.
我不开心的时候就很开心
I am happy when I'm unhappy.
维尼·丹尼尔
Vinnie Daniel.
你知道怎么做松饼吗
You know how to make a muffin?
在马克手下负责数据
Mark's numbers guy.
怎么洗衣服
Do you even know how
-你总知道吧  铺床呢  -够了
- to do laundry? Make a bed? - Okay...
维尼小时候
Vinnie lost his father
他父亲在一起暴力犯罪中丧命
to a violent crime when he was young.
跟马克一样  他也不谈这事
Just like Mark, he didn't talk about it.
我不谈那事
I don't talk about that.
辛西娅没开玩笑
Cynthia's no joke.
她真的可以把他弄去佛蒙特
She could actually make him move to Vermont.
她都可以让我系安全带
I mean, she made me start wearing a seatbelt.
-你想让我  -波特·柯林斯
- Hey, you want me to... - Porter Collins.
前奥林匹克划船手  读了布朗大学
Former Olympic rower who went to Brown.
他在前一家公司就跟鲍姆合作
He worked with Baum at a previous firm
他弄不明白怎么没人听鲍姆的
and couldn't figure out why no one listened to Baum.
他什么好点子都有
The guy with all the good ideas.
抱歉  我想你找错FrontPoint了
Sorry. I think you have the wrong FrontPoint.
因为这幢楼里
'Cause there is another
还有一家FrontPoint  搞债券的
FrontPoint in this same building that is bonds.
至于丹尼·摩西
And Danny Moses.
这伙人里最乐观的
The optimist of the bunch.
也是做交易的好手
And a hell of a trader.
这是大家能忍受他无来由乐观的唯一原因
Which is the only reason they put up with his bullshit optimism.
好奇怪的来电
That was a weird call.
你接个打错的电话时间都比别人长
You take longer with a wrong number than anybody else.
是德意志银行的那家伙
It was this guy from Deutsche
说什么关于做空房地产债券的
who was talking about shorting housing bonds.
说到一半
And then in the middle of the
我才意识到他找的是另一家FrontPoint
call I realized he had the wrong FrontPoint.
然后  因为他想找八楼的那家
And then... 'Cause he wanted the one on the 8th floor.
他想做空房地产债券
He wanted to short housing bonds?
每天得有五次
Uh-huh. That happens like five times a day
找FrontPoint找错的
that somebody gets the wrong FrontPoint.
-我们应该改名  -慢着
- We should change our name. - Wait. Wait.
他想做空房地产债券吗
He wanted to short housing bonds?
什么人会反赌房地产啊
Who bets against housing?
ABX现在多少
What's the ABX at?
什么是ABX
What's ABX?
用来追踪次级抵押证券价值的指数
It tracks subprime mortgage bond value.
回去歇着吧
Go back to sleep.
ABX现在是
The ABX is at, uh...
下跌了  过去一年下跌了三个点
Wow, it's down! It's down three points since last year.
太奇怪了  我还没听到这方面的风声呢
That's weird. I haven't heard a peep about that.
这家伙叫什么名字
What was this guy's name?
杰瑞德·温尼特  温尼特
Jared Vennett. Vennett.
没错  这些幸运的混蛋
That's right. These lucky sons of bitches
通过一通错误来电知道了华尔街史上的
caught wind of one of the best trades in Wall Street history
最佳交易
from a wrong number.
他们该给我那个蠢货助理分10%
They should have paid 10% to my fuckstick assistant.
他叫杰瑞德·温尼特  温尼特
His name was Jared Vennett. Vennett.
德意志银行的杰瑞德·温尼特
Jared Vennett from Deutsche.
听着就很肤浅
Sounded very sketchy.
听起来像个蠢货
Sounds like a douchebag.
你闻到了吗
Do you smell that?
我闻到钱的味道
I smell money.
这就是你们的基本抵押贷款
This is your basic mortgage...
好的  你好
Okay, hi. How are you?
请坐
Have a seat.
好的  德意志银行的温尼特先生
Okay, Mr. Vennett from Deutsche Bank.
有什么
What do we have?
给你
There you go.
你跟多少人谈过这笔交易
So, how many people have you talked to about this trade?
有那么几个  好几个都感兴趣
A few. There's definitely some interest.
-不行  -老板会收拾我
- No! - My boss would have my ass...
-不行  -你疯了吗  杰瑞德
- N.O.! - You crazy, Jared?
-你疯了  -滚蛋
- Get lost. - Fuck you.
所以你就来找我们谈  打错的电话
Which is why you're here talking to us, a wrong number.
听起来确实很多人感兴趣
Sounds like there's a lot of interest.
好吧  有些人请我们来
All right. A few people have invited us in
就是想笑话这笔交易  你们也是吗
just to laugh at me on this deal. Is that you?
就为了笑话我吗
Is that what this is?
不是的
That's not what this is.
只是马克想这样
That's just how Mark is.
-说说你的想法  -抱歉
- Let's see what you got. - I'm sorry.
你闻到了吗  那是什么
You smell that? What is that?
-什么  -那是什么味道
- What? - What's that smell?
你的古龙水
Your cologne?
不是
No.
机遇
Opportunity.
不  是钱
No. Money.
好吧
Okay.
-我闻到钱的味道  -好吧
- I smell money. - Okay.
-克里斯  见鬼  -抱歉
- Chris, God damn it. - Sorry.
这就是你们的基本抵押债券
This is your basic mortgage bond.
好吧  一开始很简单
All right? The originals were simple.
就是上千笔AAA级抵押贷款捆绑起来
They were just thousands of AAA mortgages bundled together,
由美国政府担保
guaranteed by the U.S. Government.
现代的却不一样了
The modern ones are different.
都是私人的  由各级别贷款打包而成
They're private. And they're made up of layers of tranches.
tranche是一个法语词
表示"东西的一部分"
最上面一级  AAA  最先给付
The highest level, AAA, is getting paid first.
最低级  B级  最后给付
The lowest rated, B, is getting paid last,
最先承担违约
taking on defaults first.
很明显  如果你买B级就可以赚更多钱
Now, obviously, if you're buying B's, you could make more money.
但有些风险
But they're a little risky.
有时它们会违约
Sometimes they fail.
克里斯
Chris?
到某个时候  这些B级和BB级
Somewhere along the line, these B's and BB's
就从有一点风险
went from a little risky
变成了狗屎  垃圾箱在哪儿
to dog shit. Where's the trash?
就在你身后
It's right behind you.
我指的是信贷评分的最低分
I'm talking rock-bottom FICO scores.
无需收入证明
No income verification.
浮动利率  狗屁
Adjustable rates. Dog shit!
违约率已经从一个百分点上升到了四个
The default rates are already up from 1% to 4%, fellas.
如果升到八个  肯定会升到八个
And if they rise to 8%, and they will,
这些评级BBB的债券就会一文不值
a lot of these BBB's are going to zero, too.
这  你离太近了
And that... You're too close.
这就是机遇
...is an opportunity.
好吧
Okay.
你是说违约率达到8%债券就会崩盘
You're saying that at 8% the bonds fail
现在已经4%了吗
and we are already at 4%?
对
That's right.
达到8%  世界末日就来临了
If they go to 8%, it's Armageddon?
对  是这样
Yeah. That's right.
为什么没人谈起过
How come nobody's talking about this?
你确定没有算错
You're completely sure of the math?
看看他  他是我的宽客
Look at him. That's my quant.
你的什么
Your what?
我的计量金融师
My quantitative!
我的数学专家  好好看看
My math specialist. Look at him.
发现特别之处了吗  看他的脸就知道
You notice anything different about him? Look at his face.
这也太种族主义了
That's pretty racist.
看他精明的双目  给你个提示
Look at his eyes! I'll give you a hint.
他姓杨
His name's Yang!
他在中国拿过全国数学联赛冠军
He won a national math competition in China!
他甚至不会说英语
He doesn't even speak English!
我确定没算错
Yeah, I'm sure of the math.
其实我姓姜  而且我会说英语
Actually, my name's Jiang and I do speak English.
杰瑞德喜欢说我不会
Jared likes to say I don't
因为他觉得这显得我的计算更加可信
because he thinks it makes me seem more authentic.
而且我在全国数学联赛拿的是亚军
And I got second in that national math competition.
所以你要提供给我们机会做空这堆积木
So you're offering us a chance to
怎么实施
short this pile of blocks? How?
利用信用违约掉期
With something called a credit default swap.
就好比债券的保险  如果崩盘
It's like insurance on the bond, and if it goes bust
你可以获利十倍  甚至二十倍
you can make 10-to-1, even 20-to-1 return.
现在崩盘已经在悄然发生
And it's already slowly going bust!
十倍  二十倍  不可能
10-to-1? 20-to-1? No way.
没有人会注意到
And no one's paying attention.
没有人在意
No one is paying attention!
因为银行正忙着卖这些债券
Because the banks are too busy getting paid obscene fees
好赚黑心钱
to sell these bonds.
等等  你就是银行的  你为银行工作
But wait. You are the bank. You work for the bank.
你的提成应该很有油水吧
I bet your margins are pretty nice and fat.
我们不谈我的提成
Let's not talk about my margins, by the way.
有油水  真是顶高帽子
Being nice and fat, that's a nice shirt. Do they make it for men?
你不是银行的人吗
Aren't you the bank?
我在银行工作  但是我有不同的想法
I work for the bank. I don't think like a bank.
不管大银行小银行  都是为了赚钱对吧
Big bank, small bank, I like to make money. All right?
这么说吧
Let me put it this way.
我站在着火的房子面前
I'm standing in front of a burning house...
问你买不买火险
and I'm offering you fire insurance on it.
这些相关债券真像你说的那么糟糕
How can these underlying bonds be as bad as you say?
这不合法吧
It wouldn't be legal.
没人知道内部情况
Nobody knows what's in them.
没人知道这些债券包括了哪些资产
Nobody knows what's in the bonds.
我见过一些含有65%AAA资产的债券
I've seen some that are 65% AAA-rated
其实内部95%都由
that I know for a fact are filled with 95%
信贷评分低于550的次贷垃圾充数
subprime shit with FICOs below 550!
滚出去
Get the fuck out of here.
看来你们还不够吃惊
You want me to really blow your mind?
当一款债券被认为风险太高时
When the market deems a bond too risky to buy,
你觉得我们怎么处理
what do you think we do with it?
猜猜看
Take a guess.
不知道  你告诉我
I don't know. You tell me.
你当我们只是书面上入个库  其实不然
All right. You think we just warehouse it on the books? No.
我们把一堆这样卖不掉的烂债券
We just repackage it with a bunch of other shit
重新包装成担保债务凭证
that didn't sell and put it into a CDO.
-担保债务凭证  -没错
- A CDO? - Yes. A CDO.
那是什么
What is that?
我们会把卖不出的B级
This is where we take a bunch of B's,
BB级和BBB级的债券
BB's and BBB's that haven't sold,
堆在一起
and we put them in a pile.
堆得足够多了
And when the pile gets large enough,
看起来就极具多样性了
the whole thing is suddenly considered diversified
德意志银行
评级机构的混蛋们就把它评为
and the whores at the rating agency give it
含有92%到93%AAA级资产的债券
a 92%-93% AAA rating,
没有人怀疑
no questions asked.
等等  什么  再说一遍
Hold it. What? Say that again.
担保债务凭证
A collateralized debt obligation.
这是很重要的概念
It's important to understand because it's what allowed
因为它会让房地产危机成为全国金融危机
a housing crisis to become a nationwide economic disaster.
让世界名厨安东尼·伯尔顿来为你解释
Here's world-famous chef Anthony Bourdain to explain.
我是个厨师  周日下午
Okay, I'm a chef on a Sunday afternoon
正在大餐馆定着菜单
setting the menu at a big restaurant.
我周五订了鱼
I ordered my fish on Friday,
就好比是迈克尔·柏利做空的抵押债券
which is the mortgage bond that Michael Burry shorted.
但有些新鲜的鱼没卖掉
But some of the fresh fish doesn't sell.
我也不知道为什么  也许是因为
I don't know why. Maybe it just
大比目鱼和海豚一样聪明
came out halibut has the intelligence of a dolphin.
那我怎么办呢
So, what am I going to do?
把没卖掉的鱼  就好比是BBB级债券
Throw all this unsold fish, which is the BBB level of the bond,
全部扔掉  承受损失吗
in the garbage and take the loss?
我不干
No way.
我是个狡猾的道德包袱又重的厨师
Being the crafty and morally onerous chef that I am,
不管什么卖不掉的坏食材
whatever crappy levels of the bond I don't sell,
我都丢进炖海鲜里
I throw into a seafood stew.
它们不再是不新鲜的鱼肉  是崭新的菜
See, it's not old fish. It's a whole new thing!
你吃的其实是捕上来三天的大比目鱼
And the best part is they're eating 3-day-old halibut.
这就是担保债务凭证
That is a CDO.
我想知道  这些债券是怎么过审的
I just need to know, how could these possibly be collated?
你就像爱冒险的朵拉一样
Somehow you're like Dora the Explorer
《爱冒险的朵拉》:美国动画片
成为了第一个发觉的人
and you're the first person who found this thing.
等等  先别吵
Hold on. Hold on.
你是不是说抵押债券是骗人把戏
So mortgage bonds are dog shit,
担保债务凭证是包装过的骗人把戏
CDOs are dog shit wrapped in cat shit.
是的  就是这样
Yeah, that's right.
各大机构对于担保债务凭证的态度
Institutions treat these
就好像他们如国库券一般稳健
CDOs like they're as solid as treasury bonds,
但他们就要坍塌了
and they're going to zero.
这不可能  单单去年
No. That can't be right. There were $500 billion
就有五千亿的房地产债券售出
in housing bonds sold last year alone.
你是说评级机构  银行和狗屁政府
The rating agencies, the banks, the fucking government,
都坐视不管吗
you're saying they're all asleep at the wheel?
是的  我在的部门一直都是这样干的
Yeah. My whole department's long on this stuff.
他们叫我小鸡仔  叫我泡沫男孩
They call me Chicken Little. They call me Bubble Boy.
A级的崩溃了  B级的也崩溃了
A's, zero. B's, zero.
BB评级和BBB评级的都崩溃了
BB's, zero. BBB's, zero.
然后那件事就发生了
And then that happens.
什么事
What is that?
倒塌的正是美国房地产市场
That's America's housing market.
谢谢
Thank you.
说的太棒了  杰瑞德
Fuckin' A, Jared.
闭上你的臭嘴
Shut your fucking mouth.
-一起出去玩  -好的
- ...hang out with you. - Good. Okay.
鼓起勇气来做  我们可以成为朋友
Sack up, do the deal. Let's be friends.
我们再考虑考虑  谢谢
We will see. Thank you.
-别跟我说这些客套话  -好吧
- Don't bullshit me. - All right.
你要拒绝了  是吗
You're gonna say no, aren't you?
不是  我只是在权衡
No. No, I'm just evaluating right now.
谢谢你来和我们说
Thank you. Thank you for coming in.
再见  杰瑞德
Bye, Jared.
我不喜欢他说的
I don't like it.
他在耍我们
He's playing us.
他在耍我们  他太会表演了
He's playing us. He's got too much skin in the game
甚至背弃了自己的职位
and he's dumping his position.
万一他说得对呢
What if he's right?
你希望他是对的
You want him to be right.
我当然希望
Yes, I do.
银行收我们25%的信用卡利率
The banks have given us 25% interest rates on credit cards.
学生贷款也压榨我们
They have screwed us on student loans
让我们永远在底层不能翻身
that we can never get out from under.
然后这个人进来和我说
Then this guy walks into my office and says
那些银行太贪心  背离了市场
those same banks got greedy, they lost track of the market,
而我则可以从他们的愚蠢中获利
and I can profit off of their stupidity?
我真他妈希望他是对的
Fuck, yeah, I want him to be right!
你怎么都不讨厌他
How come you don't hate this guy?
他是你教我们不要信任的典型啊
He's everything you taught us not to trust.
我讨厌不起来  他对于自己的利益
I can't hate him. He is so transparent
非常坦诚  我甚至有点敬佩他
in his self-interest that I kind of respect him.
如果是从他那买车  那我肯定不干
Would I buy a car from him? No.
但是他对房贷市场的分析对不对
Is he right about the mortgage market?
-不对  -我们研究研究
- No. - Let's find out. Let's find out.
这是两个很简单的问题
Look. It's two very simple questions.
房地产泡沫存在吗
Is there a housing bubble?
如果存在  银行面临多大的危机
And if there is, how exposed are the banks?
好吧
Yeah. Okay.
我们也要马上行动
Let's get on this quickly too.
因为如果他是对的
Because if he's right,
手握几百万债券的
every loser with a couple million
亏损者们都会疯狂抛售的
bucks and a fund is gonna be jumping on this.
我们走
Let's go.
就在那个早上
Just that morning...
摩根大通  摩根大通
JPMorgan Chase. JPMorgan Chase.
查理·盖乐
好了  别一个劲摩根大通了
Okay. Stop saying "JPMorgan Chase".
我有很好的预感
I got a good feeling about this.
但这只是个会面
It's just a meeting though, you know?
杰米·希普利
这只是普通的会面  就好像
It's just a meeting. It's something like...
人们总是在开会
people have meetings all the time. You know?
喝着咖啡开个会
People drink their coffee, they have a meeting.
-是布朗菲尔德基金吗  -是的
- Brownfield Fund? - Yes!
-你好  -泰德你好
- Hey. Hello. - Ted.
我是克里斯  我代泰德来的
Chris. I'm on Ted's desk.
克里斯  好吧
Chris. Okay.
-我是查理  查理·盖勒  -查理你好
- I'm Charlie, Charlie Geller. - Charlie.
-我是杰米·希普利  你好  -杰米你好
- Jamie Shipley. Hi. - Jamie.
很高兴可以加入你们的交易平台
We're so excited to get set up on your trading platform.
好的
Cool.
在这坐一会儿
Here, have a seat a second.
好的
All right.
泰德让我做点会前准备
So, I... Ted had asked me to do some meeting prep.
但是我找不到你们的营销资料
But I couldn't find any marketing material on you guys.
我们刚从博尔德搬过来
We just moved here from Boulder.
-是的  -知道了
- Yeah. - Got it.
能看看你们的报价文件吗
Could we see some of your offering documents?
布朗菲尔德是自费成立的
Well, Brownfield is its own money.
-是我们自己的投资  -是的
- It's our money. - Yeah.
可以说说你们掌管多少资产吗
Can you tell us how much you manage?
当然  我们现在有三千万
Of course. We're doing $30 million right now.
但是四年前刚起步的时候只有十一万
Um, but we started four years ago with $110,000.
所以你也能看得出  效益很显著
So, as you can see, that's pretty phenomenal returns.
我们想和摩根大通签订ISDA协议
We want to get an ISDA agreement with JPMorgan so we can
来做长期期权
deal in long-term options.
-真棒  -是的
- That's really cool. - Yeah.
ISDA协议: 保护专业投资者间进行高端交易  排除业余人士
没有ISDA协议  做高风险交易如同天方夜谭
真的做得很好
That is so cool.
谢谢
Thank you.
但你们没达到签ISDA协议的资金门槛
But you guys are under the capital requirements for an ISDA.
多少钱
By how much?
十四亿七千万  是笔大数目
Uh... One billion four hundred seventy million, so... a lot.
我们是不是看起来很傻
This makes us look bad, doesn't it,
连资金要求都不知道
that we didn't know what the capital requirements were?
确实不太好
Uh... It's not great.
但是
But, uh,
保持现在的盈利
keep up those returns and give us a call
等达到要求了可以再联系我们
way down the line. You know.
好吗
Okay?
-好的  -谢谢你  克里斯
- Okay. - Thanks, Chris.
祝你们过得愉快
Have a good one, guys.
谢谢  克里斯
Thank you, Chris.
该死
Shit!
谁会把会面时间
Who the fuck schedules a meeting
-定在下午四点五十啊  -天啊
- 4:50 in the afternoon? - Oh, my, God.
太伤人了
That was so painful.
老兄  美国银行和贝尔斯登甚至没回电
Dude, B of A and Bear didn't even return our calls.
连该死的美联银行都拒绝了我们
And even fucking Wachovia blew us off, man!
我知道
I know.
这都是其他没有通过这关的
Here's the prospectuses of all the other losers
失败者们留下的募股文件
who didn't make it past the lobby.
我干不下去了
I don't think I can do this anymore. You know.
我还年轻  我还能改变一下我的生活
I'm young, yet. I can still do something with my life.
我想念科罗拉多  那里的大麻好多了
I miss Colorado anyway. The weed's better.
先生们  请你们离开
Gentlemen, I need you to leave.
是的  我们这就走  我们走吧
Yep, yep, we're going. Let's go.
看这个  看这个
Look at this. Look at this.
这个人说房地产市场是巨大的泡沫
This guy says that the housing market's a giant bubble.
好了  其实这部分不完全符合事实
Okay, so this part isn't totally accurate, you know.
我们不是在拒绝了我们的银行大厅里
We didn't find Jared Vennett's housing bubble pitch
发现的杰瑞德·温尼特的房地产泡沫宣传册
in the lobby of a bank that rejected us.
事实是
The truth is, um,
有个朋友和查理说起
a friend had told Charlie about it, and I read about it
我在《格兰特利率观察》上读到的
in Grant's Interest Rate Observer.
真疯狂
This is crazy.
这东西好疯狂
This is crazy stuff.
天啊  他说投资基于信用违约掉期的
Shit, he's saying that there's 10-to-1 returns
住房抵押贷款支持证券可以带来十倍的收益
on credit default swaps for mortgage-backed securities?
而且整个房地产市场就要崩溃了
And the whole housing market is about to collapse?
对于杰米和查理来说
For Jamie and Charlie, the housing market
房地产市场末日的预言如同音乐一般悦耳
doomsday prediction was music to their ears.
快乐只因今日寻得挚友  于我心中
I'm so happy, coz today I found my friend, they're in my head.
他们起初在杰米的车库里创业时
They had started working out of Jamie's garage
用的是杰米驾驶帆船往返东岸
with $110,000 Jamie had saved
积攒下的十一万美元
taking sailboats up and down the East Coast.
我们的投资方案很简单
Our investment strategy was simple.
人们不愿预想坏事的发生
People hate to think about bad things happening,
所以他们总是会低估发生的可能性
so they always underestimate their likelihood.
他们的方案简单而精明
Their strategy was simple and brilliant.
正如他所说
What he said.
杰米和查理发现市场愿以极低的价格出售
Jamie and Charlie found markets will sell options very cheaply
自认为不可能发生的事情的期权
on things they think will never happen.
所以如果他们错了  损失也不大
So when they were wrong, they were wrong small,
但如果是对的  就能大赚一笔
but when they were right, they were right big.
几年内他们就把十一万变成了三千万
Within a few years they had turned $110,000 into $30 million.
然后他们就去了纽约
But then it was time to go to New York City.
但到现在为止  进展不太好
And so far, it wasn't going very well.
如果真的有利可图呢
So what if it does seem interesting. No...
没有银行愿意和我们签ISDA协议
No bank will give us our ISDA.
我们没救了
We're dead in the water.
这些交易完全做不起来
These kind of trades are totally out of the question.
我们可以给本打电话
We got to call Ben.
我们给本打电话吧
Let's call Ben!
本·瑞科特曾在大通银行新加坡分部当交易员
Ben Rickert was a former trader in Singapore
后来厌恶了这一切  退出了金融业
for Chase who quit the whole game in disgust.
他是杰米住在科罗拉多时的邻居
He happened to be Jamie's neighbor when they were in Colorado
二人的相遇缘于遛狗
and they met walking dogs.
但本很悲观
But Ben was dark.
他不仅觉得整个系统会崩溃
He didn't just think the whole system would fail.
他觉得整个世界都会沦陷
He thought the whole world was going down.
本·瑞科特
里面的蔬菜都是从我花园里新摘的
Every one of these vegetables is fresh from my garden.
你们应该经营起自己的花园
You guys should start your own garden.
首先你要去除土壤里的石油化学物质
What you got to do is get your soil off the petrochemicals.
我用木屑和肥料来恢复土壤
I used wood ash and urine to help restore the soil.
它们会产生硝酸铵
It creates ammonium nitrate.
种子很重要
Seeds are gonna be the new currency.
不要买孟山都的弗兰肯种子
And not those Franken-seeds from Monsanto.
要有机的健康种子
I'm talking about good, healthy, organic seeds.
为自己种个菜园
Make yourself a garden.
-学会依靠土地生活  -你疯了
- Learn to live off the land. - You're a fucking lunatic.
本有在大银行工作的经验
Ben had real experience in a big bank.
杰米和查理甚至连
Jamie and Charlie had
一个曼哈顿银行的卫生间都没去过
never even been in a Manhattan bank bathroom.
而本已经厌倦了银行业
But Ben was done with the banking world.
他很聪明
He was very clear.
好了  我们得算算数据
All right, let's crunch some numbers
然后再谈给本打电话的事
and then maybe we'll talk about calling Ben.
我们总是在算数据
We're always crunching numbers.
要算到什么时候
When haven't we crunched the numbers?
我们这次要算得再精细些
We're gonna crunch the numbers like harder...
请你们快离开
I need you out of here.
好的  马上
Of course. One second.
是  我们这就走
Yes, ma'am. We're going.
我讨厌这样浪费时间
Oh, God. I hate this. This is a total waste of time.
拜托  能不能放松点
Oh, come on. Would you relax?
城外45分钟车程就有个住宅区
There's a housing development 45 minutes outside town.
马克让我们先去查查看
Mark wants us to check that out first.
我希望路上有古巴餐馆
Well, I hope there are some Cuban restaurants on the way there.
我听说迈阿密的古巴菜很棒
Because I heard the Cuban food is amazing in Miami.
别跟我叽叽喳喳抱怨痛苦
Please don't be chipper in the face of me being miserable.
真的会让我讨厌你
It really makes me hate you.
想吃东西怎么能叫叽叽喳喳
How is wanting to eat good food being chipper?
有人吗
Hello?
有人在家吗
这些房子能卖多少
What do these go for?
四十二万五千一栋
$425,000 each?
《迈阿密先驱报》
你好  有何贵干
What's up, man? What do you want?
你好  我正在调查
Hello. I'm surveying
拖欠房贷超过90天的贷款人
mortgage owners who are over 90 days delinquent.
我要找哈维·哈普西
I'm looking for a Harvey Humpsey.
你找我房东的狗干嘛
You want my landlord's dog?
你的房东
Your landlord filled out
用狗的名字申请了房贷吗
his mortgage application using his dog's name?
看起来是的
I guess so.
等一下  那个混蛋没有还贷款吗
Wait, has that asshole not been paying his mortgage?
可我一直有交房租啊
'Cause I've been paying my rent.
是的  他拖欠贷款超过90天了
Well, yeah, he is over 90 days delinquent.
说真的
Seriously, man,
我是不是得搬走了
am I gonna have to leave?
可我刚搞定孩子上学的事情
'Cause my kid just got settled in school, man.
你好吗
Hey. How are ya?
我叫肯
My name's Ken.
你是肯吗
You're Ken?
你应该跟你的房东谈谈了
Um, you should talk to your landlord about that.
对不起  我没有更多信息了
I'm sorry, I don't have any more information.
但是你...
But you, um...
祝你过得愉快  再见  肯
You have a great day. See ya, Ken.
到处都是书
There's books everywhere!
Books everywhere?
说真的  我们会有事吗
Seriously, man, is everything gonna be okay?
你应该给他打电话
You should... You should call him.
给他打个电话
You should give him a call.
这不是我的错  我交房租了啊...
It's not my fault, dude. I've been paying...
你好
Hello!
看起来走得很急啊
Looks somebody just left.
看  他们就把电视拿走了
Look. All they took was the TV.
这很反常
It's weird.
他们连台面都没有清理
They didn't even clean out the counter.
逾期通知
上帝啊
Oh, God.
对不起
这里就像切尔诺贝利
It's like Chernobyl.
这里有上百栋房子吧
There's like a hundred houses.
真正住在这里的可能四个人都不到
There can't be four people living here.
-他妈的  -见鬼
- Oh, fuck that! - Shit!
《沙娜拉传奇》
他在里面七个小时了
He's been in there for seven hours.
他怎么上厕所呢
Where does he go to the bathroom?
赛恩净值
我听说他崩溃了
I heard he had a breakdown.
他要让基金破罐破摔了
He's letting the fund tank.
我有个在曼哈顿的朋友说...
My buddy in Manhattan said...
柏利博士的办公室
Dr. Burry's office.
不是  他比较喜欢别人给他发邮件
No, he actually prefers that you email him.
不好意思
Excuse me.
菲尔兹先生...
Mr. Fields, Mr...
-劳伦斯  -该死
- Hi, Lawrence. - Holy shit!
我们不相信你对宏观经济的
We have no confidence in your ability to identify
判断能力
macroeconomic trends.
你们飞到这里来就跟我说这个  为什么
You flew here to tell me that? Why?
谁都能看出房地产市场出现了泡沫
Anyone can see that there is a real estate bubble.
事实上  谁都没看出来
Actually, no one can see a bubble.
这正是泡沫存在的原因
That's what makes it a bubble.
他们太蠢了  劳伦斯
That's dumb, Lawrence.
总是有迹象的
There's always markers.
房贷欺诈的数量
Mortgage fraud has
是2000年的五倍
quintupled since 2000
而人均收入没有提高
and the average take-home pay is flat,
但房价却猛涨
but home prices are soaring.
这意味着这些房地产都是负债  而不是资产
That means the homes are debt, not assets.
所以圣何塞的迈克·柏利
So Mike Burry of San Jose, a guy who
这个人在"超级剪刀"理发  从来不穿鞋
gets his hair cut at Supercuts and doesn't wear shoes,
比格林斯潘和保尔森懂的还多
knows more than Alan Greenspan and Hank Paulson.
是迈克·柏利博士  没错  我是懂的多
Dr. Mike Burry, yes, he does.
真有趣  真有趣
That's cute. That's cute.
你在讽刺我们吗  迈克
Are you being sarcastic with us, Mike?
劳伦斯
Lawrence,
我不会讽刺
I don't know how to be sarcastic.
我不会开玩笑
I don't know how to be funny. I don't know how to
我不擅长与人打交道
work people.
我...
I...
我只擅长跟数字打交道
I just know how to read numbers.
你现在做空的仓位有多少
How big is your short position right now?
只有十三亿
Just $1.3 billion.
溢价呢
And the premiums?
我们每年
Well, we pay, uh,
大概要付八千到九千万
roughly $80 to 90 million
虽然有点高
each year, which is high,
但是我是第一个做这种交易的人
but I was the first to do this trade.
等着瞧吧  肯定会赚回来的
Watch. It will pay.
我可能下手有点早  但是我没做错
I may have been early, but I'm not wrong.
没有区别  根本没有区别  迈克
It's the same thing. It's the same thing, Mike!
你管理的基金有差不多5.5亿吧
You're managing a fund of, what, $555 million?
用不了六年就都没了
In six years, it'll all be gone.
只在这一项赌注上
On one bet.
不会的  等到2007年第二季度
No, the second quarter
浮动利率开始执行的时候
of '07 is when the adjustable rates kick in.
违约率就会飞涨
The defaults will skyrocket.
是啊  只有你这么说
Yeah. Says you.
在那之前有多少可以赎回
How much is eligible for withdrawal before they do?
我是说下两个季度
Say, in the next two quarters.
如果你的投资人恐慌了
If your investors panic.
3.2亿吧
$302 million?
我...
I...
我的天哪  迈克
My God, Mike.
没有人会撤资的  那相当于自杀
No one will pull out. That would be suicide.
我是说  今年我已经赔了17%了
I mean, I'm down 17% for the year.
但如果他们相信我  他们确实信我  因为
But if they trust me, and they trust me, because...
没有人相信你  没有人
No one trusts you! No one!
我给投资人们发了几封邮件
I sent several emails to my investors
让他们知道
letting them know that the...
等到2007年第二季度
...the second quarter of '07 is when our
我们在房地产上的投资就会看到回报了
housing positions show returns and...
我说得非常清楚
I've been very clear.
他们会撤资的
People will withdraw their money.
劳伦斯  那样做就太蠢了  我是说
Lawrence, that would be so stupid. I mean, the...
如果基金资本流失过多
If the fund's capitals drop too much,
掉期就会失效
then the swaps contracts are voided.
银行会拿走全部的抵押物
And then the banks get to keep all of the collateral.
-等一下  -所有的抵押物
- Wait a minute. Wait. - All of it.
合同会自动失效
The contracts are voided?
他妈的
Holy shit!
你这个畜生
Oh, motherfucker!
迈克尔
Michael?
把我的钱还给我
Give me my money back.
迈克尔  你听到了吗  我要你还钱
Michael, do you hear me? I want my money back.
把我的钱他妈的还给我
Give me my fucking money back...
你这个混蛋
...you motherfucker.
市场目前正处于一个小低谷中
The market's in an itsy-bitsy little gully right now.
就像大家说的  "好像有点太疯狂了"
It's like everybody said, "Okay, that was crazy."
"那就先冷静一下吧"
"Let's just all calm down."
那栋房子刚建好那年我把它卖了35万
I sold that house for $350,000 the year it was built.
两年之后  它值48万
Two years later, $480,000.
一年半之前是58.5万
Then $585,000 maybe 18 months ago.
这对夫妻去年花了65万买下了它
This couple bought it for $650,000 last year.
看现在的情况  他不得不出手了
He'd let it go for that.
约翰
Hi, John.
不  不用
No, no, no.
虽然非常心疼  但他还是会出手的
It will break his heart, but he'll let it go.
他为什么要卖掉房子
Why is he selling?
他们夫妻俩现在都没工作
Neither one's working right now.
玛琳  你是说他们有卖房的理由是吗
Marlene, you'd say they're motivated, right?
跟这附近其他人的理由一样充分
As motivated as one can be in this neighborhood.
左边这家  我觉得他们也可能很积极
This house on the left, I would say they're probably motivated.
天啊  看起来积极卖房的人不少啊
Wow, a lot of people seem very motivated.
这只是个小低谷
Oh, it's just the gully.
就这样  没什么
That's all. Just...
大家只是有点紧张
Just nerves.
那么我们要去看哪一家
So where do we stand?
我还得跟我太太商量商量
I need to talk to my wife. Um...
市场不会一直这样的
This market won't last.
我能找个房贷经纪人谈谈吗
Actually, could I talk to a mortgage broker?
你有认识的还不错的吗
Anybody you recommend? Anybody you like.
当然  我认识几个  绝对没问题
Yes, yes, I have someone. Absolutely.
那个贱人当然喜欢我了
Yeah, bitch better like me.
因为我她才有钱去卡布度假
Sent her ass to Cabo.
摩根斯坦利是要招募我们吗
So is Morgan Stanley recruiting us? Is that it?
不是的  对冲基金的所有权属于银行
Oh, no. No. The bank owns our hedge fund,
但是我们并不是银行的一部分
but we're not really part of it.
我们对金融公司进行投资
We invest in financial service companies
现在想了解一下住房贷款业务的情况
and we're trying to understand the residential mortgage business.
你每个月能做多少笔贷款
How many loans do you write each month?
-大概60笔吧  -没错
- About 60. - Yeah.
四年前的情况呢
What was it four years ago?
10笔吧
Ten...
也可能是15笔
Maybe 15.
我以前只是个酒保  现在我游艇都有了
Yeah, I was a bartender. Now I own a boat.
你有一艘...
You own a...
那这些贷款里面有多少是浮动利率的
So how many of these are adjustable-rate mortgages?
-大部分都是  -是的
- Well, most. - Oh, yeah.
我看90%都是浮动利率
Yeah, I'd say about 90%.
在这种贷款上的提成几年前就飞涨了
The bonuses on those skyrocketed a few years ago.
浮动利率就是我们的金矿
Adjustable's our bread and honey.
那有申请被拒的情况吗
So do applicants ever get rejected?
你没开玩笑吧
Seriously?
如果有申请被拒了  那我就不称职了
Look, if they get rejected, I suck at my job.
即使他们没钱也没问题
Even if they have no money?
我的公司提供"忍者"贷款
Well, my firm offers NINJA loans.
"没收入  没工作"
"No Income, No Job."
我把收入那一栏空着就好了
I just leave the income section blank if I want.
公司不介意这个的
Corporate doesn't care.
这些人就想有个住的地方  就顺其自然了
These people just want homes. And they go with the flow.
你们真行
Good for you.
你们的公司不去核实他们的财务状况吗
Your companies don't verify?
如果我周五下午签下一笔贷款
If I write a loan on Friday afternoon,
周一早上就会有大银行把它买走
a big bank will buy it by Monday lunch.
是的  我这里也差不多
Yeah. Same here.
能失陪一下吗
Could you hold on a second?
当然
Yeah.
我不明白  他们为什么这么坦白
I don't get it. Why are they confessing?
他们这不是坦白
They're not confessing.
他们是在吹牛
They're bragging.
他们清楚这些贷款的风险吗
Do people have any idea what they are buying?
我的客户主要是移民  你懂的
I focus on the immigrants, you know.
只要他们想买房
Once they find out they're getting a home,
给什么他们都会签的
they sign where you tell them to sign.
没有疑问  也不理解利率
Don't ask questions. Don't understand the rates.
-都是他妈的傻逼  -没错
- Fucking idiots. - Yeah.
你也主要做移民的生意吗
And you target immigrants, too?
移民的信用对他来说还不够糟呢
Well, their credit actually isn't bad enough for him.
我不是个跟钱过不去的人
Look, I'm a yield guy.
是这样...
Okay...
在一笔固定利率的优质房贷上
I make $2,000
我只能赚两千美元
on a fixed-rate prime loan, right?
但在浮动利率的次贷上我能赚一万美元
But I can make $10,000 on a subprime adjustable.
相信我
Trust me,
没有脱衣舞娘我现在也开不上宝马7系了
I'm not driving a 7 Series without strippers.
脱衣舞娘的信用普遍不高  但是现金充足
No one on the pole has good credit and they're all cash rich.
我记得沃伦·巴菲特也说过这样的话
I think I read Warren Buffett say something like that.
什么  谁是沃伦·巴菲特
What? Who's Warren Buffett?
你说脱衣舞娘  那种异域舞者吗
Okay, so strippers. Like exotic dancers?
对  对  对
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
一丝不挂的那种
Nude, you know, topless.
-一丝不挂的脱衣舞娘  -没错
- Strippers. - Yeah.
你能给我们介绍一个吗
Can you introduce us?
当然  没问题
Yes! Yes.
我总是申请选择性还款的浮动利率贷款
I always get option-pay adjustables.
我是个自由职业者
I'm a private contractor.
不好意思  我听不见你说什么
What? I can't hear you. I'm sorry.
我总是申请选择性还款的浮动利率贷款
I always get option-pay adjustables.
我是个自由职业者  需要一些灵活性
I'm a private contractor. I need flexibility.
那你告诉房贷公司你是做什么工作的
And you tell the mortgage company what you do?
我的申请上写的是"治疗师"
I write "Therapist".
-你可以摸我  -一直这样吗
- You can touch me. - Always?
只有在VIP包房才可以
Only in V.I.P.
不是这个  你说你总是选浮动利率贷款
No, no, no, you say you always do adjustables.
你在一套房上不止一笔贷款吗
And you have more than one loan on a property?
每个人都这样  至少在这里是这样
Everybody does. At least down here.
不好意思  你说什么
I'm sorry, what?
每个人都这样  至少在这里是这样
Everybody does. At least down here.
这样首付只要5%
That way you only put down, like, 5%.
现在房价跌了你知道吗
Prices have leveled off, though, right?
是啊  只是个低谷
Yeah. There's a gully.
你可以别晃来晃去吗  我会付你钱的
Would you mind not moving anymore? I'll still pay you.
对不起  有人看着呢
Sorry. We're not alone.
听我说  如果房价不涨了
Okay, look. If home prices don't go up,
你就不能重新贷款了
you are not going to be able to refinance.
等到利率优惠期一过
And you'll be stuck paying whatever your monthly payment is
你就会陷入高涨的月供
once it jumps up after your teaser rate expires.
月供会涨200%到300%
Your monthlies could go up 200%-300%.
詹姆斯说我总是可以重新贷款的
James says I can always refinance.
他就是个骗子
Well, he's a liar.
其实  在这种特殊情况下  詹姆斯说错了
Actually, in this particular case, James probably is wrong.
200%  我的所有贷款都这样吗
200 percent? On all my loans?
你的"所有"贷款是什么意思
What do you mean "All" Your loans?
我们说的是一套房子上的两笔贷款对吗
We're talking about two loans on one house, right?
我有五套房子
I have five houses.
还有一套公寓
And a condo.
没错  绝对有泡沫
Hey, there's a bubble.
你怎么知道的
How do you know?
相信我  给温尼特打电话
Trust me. Call Vennett,
买五千万的住房抵押贷款支持证券掉期
buy $50 million in swaps on the MBS.
有什么目标  评级BBB的Garibaldi IV
What do we got? Garibaldi IV, BBB.
马克  你确定吗
Mark, are you sure?
当然  这些都是狗屎
Yeah. Yeah, it's time to call bullshit.
-什么是狗屎  -全都是狗屎
- Bullshit on what? - Every fucking thing.
FrontPoint的电话
FrontPoint! FrontPoint!
是全美国最愤怒的对冲基金吗
Is this America's angriest hedge fund?
听我说  我有一个问题要问你
All right, listen. I got one last question for you.
你想怎么玩弄我们
How are you fucking us?
你不用说的这么难听  维尼
There's a nicer way to say that, Vinnie.
我是认真的
I'm serious.
只有你说了
We'll buy your swaps,
我们才会买你的掉期
but only if you say how you're fucking us.
我不想玩弄你们  维尼  我想吻你们啊
I'm not fucking you, Vinnie. I'm kissing you.
我要深情注视你的双眼跟你做爱  维尼
I'm looking deep into your eyes as I make love to you, Vinnie.
我把本世纪最划算的买卖送到了你的面前
I'm handing you the deal of the century on a fucking platter.
我能得到什么  很简单
What do I get out of it? Easy.
我现在的业务每个月赔两千万
I got a $20-million-a-month negative carry.
我的老板们早就想杀了我
I got bosses trying to pull the
因为他们觉得我他妈的疯了
plug because they think I'm out of my fucking mind.
明白吗
All right?
如果我们完成这笔交易
We make this trade,
这些问题就都不是问题了
those problems aren't so big anymore.
当然了  掉期市场是个不透明的黑市
And sure, swaps are a dark market,
所以价格我说了算
so I set the price.
我想定价多少就定多少
Whatever price I want.
当你们赚到钱的时候
And when you come for the payday,
我会在你们身上大赚一笔
I'm gonna rip your eyes out, I'm gonna make a fortune.
但是你们也不会在乎了  维尼
But the good news is, Vinnie, you're not gonna care
因为你们赚的更他妈多
because you're gonna make so much fucking money.
这就是我能得到的好处
That's what I get out of it.
想知道你们能得到的好处吗
Want to know what you get out of it?
你们会得到冰淇淋  巧克力  香蕉和坚果
You get the ice cream, the hot fudge, the banana, and the nuts.
现在  我是得到了些小糖粒
Right now, I get the sprinkles, and, yeah,
最后我能得到圣代顶上的那颗樱桃
if this goes through, I get the cherry.
但是你们会得到整个圣代  维尼
But you get the sundae, Vinnie.
剩下的都是你们的
You get the sundae.
好吧  我信你  谢谢
All right, I buy that. Thank you.
那怎么说
So what do you say?
-你要跟我做生意吗  -好的
- You want me to make you a market? - Yeah.
我们要买五千万的掉期
We'll take $50 million,
评级BBB的Garibaldi IV
Garibaldi IV, BBB.
准备好签字吧  我马上把合同弄好
Sharpen your pencils. I'll get the paperwork ready.
操你大爷
Fuck you, too.
太棒了
Yes!
这就对了
That's right.
天啊
Oh, man.
他的号码太多了  我总是搞不清
He has so many numbers, and I always forget
2006年5月
他喜欢用哪个  因为他太特别了
which one he prefers, because he's very specific.
从第一个开始试吧
Start with the first one.
我不知道第一个对不对
I don't know if it's the first one.
试试就知道了
Just try it.
好吧
Okay. I... Okay.
-本·瑞科特  -本  我是杰米
- Ben Rickert. - Hey, Ben. It's Jamie.
杰米  你知道你不应该打这个号码吧
Jamie, you know you're not supposed to use this line.
我说什么来着
Told you.
好吧  我们试试这14个号码里的第二个
Okay, let's try number two out of 14.
这里是本·瑞科特
Ben Rickert.
本  你为什么要挂电话  我是说
Ben, why do you do that, man? I mean...
你退休了  没人会窃听你的电话
You're a retired trader, okay? No one is listening to your calls.
国安局有520亿美元的预算
The NSA has a $52 billion budget and the ability
他们每秒能窃听数百万次通话
to monitor tens of millions of calls a second.
你觉得他们就放在那里不用吗
You think they're not using it?
我保证不在一句话里
Hey, I promise I will refrain from saying
说出本·瑞科特和"脏弹"这两个词
"Ben Rickert" And "Dirty bomb" in the same sent...
-他妈的上帝啊  -不好意思  哥们
- Jesus fucking Christ. - I'm sorry, dude.
本·瑞科特
Ben Rickert.
你有没有看我们发给你的资料  本
Did you get a chance to look at what we sent you, Ben?
是查理在讲话  我也在这里
It's Charlie. I'm here, too.
你好查理  我看了  你等等
Hi, Charlie. Yeah, I did. Hold on.
本  你还在吗
Ben, you still there?
我在
Yeah.
先生们  我实话实说
I'll be honest, gentlemen.
我被吓到了
It scared the shit out of me.
但这是好事  对吧
But that's a good thing, right?
说明这个叫温尼特的人没说错
That means this Vennett guy's not wrong.
是的  他没错
No, he's not.
那好
Cool.
和我多说点相关信息
Tell me more about these CDOs.
好  温尼特提到这些债务担保凭证
Yeah, yeah. Okay, so, you know, Vennett mentions the CDOs,
但事实上  我们看过以后
but actually, we took a look
事情比他意识到的要糟得多
and they're way worse than even he realizes.
这些数据根本说不通
These things don't make any sense!
我们甚至无法建立模型
We can't even model them.
它的数量比房贷证券要大100倍
These are 100 times bigger than the MBS.
90%为AAA评级
And 90% AAA-rated.
-是啊  -超过90%
- Yes! Exactly! - Over 90%.
你们挺厉害
It's incredible.
我仔细看了你们想做空的这些担保凭证
I took a good hard look at the CDOs you want to short.
它们就是外秀内中  彻头彻尾的垃圾
They're brilliant. Worthless. Total crap.
杰米  干得漂亮
Jamie. Very good.
怎么说呢  找垃圾投资我还挺有天赋的
What can I say? I'm good at finding shit.
那么本  我们把BB和BBB级别的做空
So, Ben, we shorted the BB's and the BBB's,
然后风险也相对比较小
and the risk is relatively low.
-回报率大概是25倍  -是的
- Payoff is, like, 25-to-1. - Yeah.
你们打电话找我干啥  我早洗手不干了
Okay, so, why are you calling me? I don't do this anymore.
是这样的  本
Look, Ben?
我们需要你帮我们拿到ISDA协议
We need you to help us get the ISDA.
ISDA协议是国际掉期与衍生品协会为国际场外衍生品交易提供的标准协议文本及其附属文件。
有了协议在手  我们才能做空
If we get a hunting license, we can short this crap.
我们知道你痛恨华尔街
And we know you hate Wall Street.
所以不会要求你替我们做交易
We're not asking you to do the trading.
我们只是想求你帮我们弄到
We're simply asking you to help us get a seat
一张开始的入场券
at the fucking table.
这可不是闹着玩的
It's a pretty ugly table, guys.
本  整个金融系统已经乱成一团
Look, Ben, the system fucked up in a big, big way here, okay?
但偶然地
And somehow, uh,
我们却抢先得到了消息
we know before anyone else.
这可是千载难逢的好机会
You know? This is a once-in-a-lifetime deal.
我在考虑
I'm thinking.
好吧  我会给德意志银行打个电话
Okay. I'll call Deutsche Bank.
谢谢你  本  谢谢
Thank you, Ben. Thank you.
那贝尔斯登公司呢  那也有些垃圾产品
And Bear. What about Bear? They have some reprehensible product.
可以  贝尔斯登肯定来者不拒
Okay. Bear will trade with anybody.
欢迎来到纽约  市长迈克尔·布隆伯格
我看看能不能把材料递交上去
All right. I'll see if I can push it through.
谢谢你  诺亚  替我们谢谢杰瑞德
Thank you, Noah. And thank Jared for us.
我们就不能进公司里签字吗
Couldn't we go inside?
就是说
Yeah, me, too.
真相如诗歌
在华盛顿某酒吧无意听到的一句话
福克斯商业新闻: 抵押贷款拖欠额度创100万新高
2007年1月11日
我是马克  我急需与维尼谈谈
Hi, this is Mark. I need to talk to Vinnie right now.
我们就想让你跟我们解释一下
We're just asking you to explain to us
你为什么耍我们
just how it is that you are fucking us,
因为我这里看到的情况
because what we are seeing...
去摩根斯坦利大厦  快
Morgan Stanley building, fast.
我们看的是同样的数据吗
Are we hooked up to the same computer screen?
这数据完全说不通
It doesn't make any sense.
维尼  听得到吗
Vinnie, you there?
马克  听得到吗
Mark, you there?
听得到  你听说了没
Yeah, did you hear?
抵押贷款拖欠额度已经破新高了
Mortgage defaults have gone through the roof.
有人跳楼了吗
Is anybody jumping off of buildings yet?
为什么跳楼  次贷债券的价格居高不下
Why would they? Subprime mortgage bond prices are up.
什么
What?
温尼特想在收市前再投入190万抵押
Vennett wants $1.9 million more in collateral by close.
温尼特想让我们追加抵押
Vennett's asking us to post collateral.
怎么回事
What the hell is going on?
不知道  但德意志银行在电话里要求付款
We don't know, but Deutsche's on the phone demanding payment.
给温尼特打电话  让这混蛋接电话
Call Vennett. Call that little shit.
给温尼特打电话  叫他赶紧滚过来
Call Vennett. Tell him to get his ass down here.
所以次级贷款断供了
So subprime loans go bad,
但它们组成的次级贷款债券
but subprime bonds, which are
反而升值了吗
made up of subprime loans, are more valuable?
我懂  但他们让我们收市前追加190万
I know. They want another $1.9 million by market close.
信用评级机构呢  穆迪公司和标普呢
What about the ratings agencies? Moody's, S&P...
债务担保凭证和房贷债券的评级下调了吗
Are they downgrading the CDOs and mortgage bonds?
信用评级机构的评级如何
Where are the ratings agencies at?
评级保持不变
They're the fucking same.
没变  还是AAA级
No, they're all still AAA.
搞什么  你这是在逗我吗
What the hell? Are you fucking kidding me?
这群混蛋  没良心的混蛋
Those fuckers! Those motherfuckers!
这些评级公司一公开上市
They go public, and all they
就只管自己的净利润
care about is their bottom line and their shit.
马克  这还没完
Hey, Mark, that's not all.
摩根斯坦利风险部门的人来了
The Morgan Stanley risk guys are here.
他们找了陶凯茜
They called in Kathy Tao.
他们想说服她卖掉咱们的掉期交易
They're trying to convince her to make us sell our swaps.
显然  他们认为套牢六年保险费
Apparently, tying up six years of insurance payments
坐等房地产崩溃
in hopes of a housing Armageddon
是一项不明智的投资
is not prudent investing.
那凯西说了什么
What did Kathy say?
还没  她一直问这是不是你的讨伐运动
Nothing yet. She keeps asking if this is one of your crusades.
那好  我想让你回到那房间
Okay, I want you to walk back in there
用冷静且礼貌的方式
and very calmly, very politely,
让这些风险评估师都他妈滚蛋
tell the risk assessors to fuck off.
然后你到标准普尔机构这和我碰面
And then meet me over at Standard & Poor's.
我们找格鲁吉亚谈谈
We're gonna talk to Georgia.
好的
All right. Okay.
让杰瑞德·温尼特给我滚过来
Get that fuck Jared Vennett in this office.
看我待会打爆他脑袋
I'm gonna bash his fucking head in.
先生们
Uh, gentlemen?
我刚和马克·鲍姆谈过了  他让你们滚蛋
I spoke with Mark Baum. He says to fuck off.
百老汇大道25号  标准普尔评级机构
我啥都看不清
I can't see a damn thing.
我的眼科医生一直都很忙
My eye doctor's always busy.
所以我只好接受任何可行的预约
I end up taking any appointment they'll give me,
然后整个上午就这么荒废了
and then the whole morning gets shot to hell!
那么
So...
好的
All righty,
顶尖基金公司的朋友们
FrontPoint Partners,
标准普尔有什么能帮到你们吗
how can Standard & Poor's help you?
我们不明白为什么
Well, we don't understand why
评级机构还没有下调次贷债券的评级
the ratings agencies haven't downgraded subprime bonds
因为债券对应的房贷  断供明显在恶化
since the underlying loans are clearly deteriorating.
断供率确实让部分人担心了
Well, the delinquency rates do have people worried,
但这波动是在我们的模型预测之内的
but they're actually within our models.
-那么…  -口说无凭
- So... - Says you.
你确信这些债券对应的房贷
...you're convinced the underlying mortgages
是可靠的吗
in these bonds are solid loans.
根据我们公司的观点  是的
That is our opinion, yes.
你看过发放贷款的数据吗
Have you looked at the loan-level data?
任何人  只要有信用评分
I mean, they're giving these loans
都能随意拿到贷款
to anybody with a credit score and a pulse.
抱歉  先生你认为我们的工作是什么
Excuse me, sir. What do you think we do here all day?
我们不确定  所以才到这里来
We're not sure. That's why we're here.
我不明白的是
Here's what I don't understand...
我们再三确认过了
We check, recheck, recheck again.
如果这些房贷债券这么稳定靠谱
If these mortgage bonds are so stable...
也许你该先检查下你朋友正不正常
Perhaps you could check your friend.
你是否有曾拒绝过
...have you ever refused to rate...
-这是痴人说梦  -我们相信这些公司
- Ma'am, that's delusional. - We stand behind them.
格鲁吉亚  你是否拒绝过给这里的
Georgia, have you ever refused to rate
任何一家公司的AAA评级
any of these bonds upper tranches AAA?
我能看看这些交易对应的材料吗
Can we see the paperwork on those deals?
我没有义务与你们
I am under no obligation to share that information
或任何人分享这些信息
with you, whoever you might be.
回答我的问题  格鲁吉亚
Just answer the question, Georgia.
你能给出一个去年里  经你查证后
Can you name one time in the past year where you checked the tape
没能获得银行想要的AAA评级的例子吗
and you didn't give the banks the AAA percentage they wanted?
如果我们不这么评
If we don't give them the ratings,
他们就会去找隔壁的穆迪评级了
they'll go to Moody's, right down the block.
若我们不配合  他们就去找我们的对手
If we don't work with them, they will go to our competitors.
这不怪我们  规则就是这么定的
Not our fault. Simply the way the world works.
-我的天  -现在你明白了吧
- Holy shit. - Yes, now you see.
我刚才什么都没说
And I never said that.
他们拿评级来卖钱
They're selling ratings for fees.
像商店一样
A ratings shop.
你们不缺钱  别贪心
You can afford to make less. Make less.
没人这么说过
Nobody said that.
而且这不是我能决定的  我有上司
And it is not my decision. I have a boss.
你在逗我吗
Are you kidding me?
我没在和你开玩笑
No, I am not "Kidding you".
如果是首次上市募股  你上级会怎么做
How'd your boss do on the IPO?
这就是你的立场吗
Is that the angle you're taking?
-只要自己不是老板  -站着说话不腰疼
- So, now, anyone who has a boss  - You’re obviously working for yourselves then.
违法都不会被追究责任吗
can't be held responsible for doing shitty and illegal things.
你还是小孩吗
What are you, four?
不  我不是四岁孩子  鲍姆先生
No, I am not four, Mr. Baum. I am not, no.
我疑惑的是你们的来这的动机是什么
And I wonder what your incentives might be.
是不是评级如果变了
Is it maybe in your best interest
对你们有好处  是吗
to have the ratings change? Is it, perhaps?
你们持有多少信用违约掉期交易
How many credit default swaps do you own? Hmm?
但这不代表我是错的
It doesn't make me wrong.
你是没错
No.
但这让你们看起来很虚伪
It just makes you a hypocrite.
操
Fuck!
房贷断供率不断上涨
Mortgage delinquencies went up
而债权担保凭证居然升值了  难以置信
and the CDOs got more valuable. Unbelievable.
-难以置信  -就是  走势太反常了
- Unbelievable. - We know. It's completely backwards.
我刚给贝尔斯登公司的一位老朋友打电话
I just called an old friend at Bear.
他连抵押债权是什么都不知道
He didn't even know what a CDO is.
是的  我刚汇给贝尔和德意志七万块
Yeah, I just had to wire Bear and Deutsche $70,000.
这太扯淡了  就像是二加二等于
It's like two plus two equals
一条鱼
fish.
这里头有黑幕  我们碰上黑幕了
It's rigged. We bought into a rigged game.
我们会输个精光
We're gonna lose everything.
然后我不得不搬回家里和我妈住
I'm gonna have to move back in with my mom.
那可不行啊
Can't do that.
我还有个灌肠的预约
All right. Well, I got a colonic appointment.
等等  本  别挂
Wait a minute. Hold on, Ben.
本  听着
Ben, look.
要么是银行还没意识到
Either the banks are clueless
这些抵押债权的真实价值
and they don't know how to value these CDOs,
要么他们都是骗子  拼命掩盖
or they're such crooks that the CDOs are worth shit
这些债券都是垃圾的真相
and they're hiding it.
我觉得咱们应该买进更多掉期
I think we should buy more swaps.
你说什么
What?
闭嘴然后付钱  咱们签过合同的
Suck it up and pay up, fellas. We made a deal.
不行  不行
No way! No!
你在逗我吗  还有脸过来
Are you fucking kidding me? You coming here to…
你认真的吗  你觉得这是闹着玩吗
Are you serious? You think this is a game?
不不不
No. No. No. No. No.
买买买
Yeah. Yeah.
不不不
No! No! No!
我说真的  一年要洗一次肠
No, seriously, a colonic once a year.
混蛋
Ass!
你现在还带个跟班了  你个混蛋
And you got a matching little butler boy, you buttfuck!
-你骂完了吗  -完了
- Are you done? - I think so, yeah.
天  骂得太起劲不小心闪了腰
God! I pulled a muscle in my back from yelling.
房贷拖欠率一直在涨
Mortgage defaults have done nothing but go up.
而你给我们的房贷证券报价却更高了
Yet you quote us a higher price on the bonds.
请你解释下  这根本说不通
Please explain that to me. There's no way that makes sense.
你这些掉期交易估算肯定有问题
There's no way you're marking these swaps appropriately.
我们为什么还要继续和你交易
Why shouldn't we back out of this trade right now?
我们达成交易那会
Didn't I say when we made
我有没有说过评级机构  证券交易所委员会
this deal that the ratings agencies, the SEC
以及大银行对即将发生的事都一头雾水
and the big banks were clueless? Didn't I say that?
-说过  -我说过吧
- Yes. - Didn't I say it?
是的  你说过  确实说过
Yes, you did. You did.
闭嘴
Shut up.
现在火上身
Now their foot's on fire,
他们反而觉得自己赚到了  你们觉得很意外吗
they think their steak is done, and you're surprised?
这不是愚蠢  是骗局
That's not stupidity. That's fraud.
愚蠢和犯法就是一个道理
Tell me the difference between stupid and illegal,
我正要把我的白痴小舅子抓起来
and I'll have my wife's brother arrested.
挺好笑的
That was funny.
我猜你还没意识到整个系统都是一头雾水
I guess you just don't realize how clueless the system really is.
是  我承认是有些见不得人的举动
Yes, there's some shady shit going down,
但相信我  这都是愚蠢导致的
but trust me, it's fuelled by stupidity!
看看你们自己
Look at yourselves.
你们证明了自己是敢于怀疑的人
You know, you pass yourself off as cynical people
却还对这个系统抱有希望吗
but you still have some faith in the system, don't you?
我不抱希望
I don't.
维尼是明白人  还有谁在乎
Well, except for Vinnie. And who gives a shit?
-不行  -听着
- No way! - Look...
要么我们是对的  要么我们大错特错
Either we're right or we're wrong in a giant, giant way.
若我们错了  我们需要找人
And if we're wrong, then we got to find someone
帮我们脱手这场交易
to help us get out of this trade.
我现在很难相信我们是对的
I'm not feeling remotely confident that we're right.
而且万一我们错了  谁会告诉我们
And if we're wrong, who's gonna tell us?
有谁能理解这东西  根本说不通
Who understands this stuff? It makes no sense!
我觉得咱们需要去拉斯维加斯
I think we need to go to Vegas.
-拉斯维加斯有什么  -拉斯维加斯吗
- What's in Vegas? - Vegas?
拉斯维加斯怎么了
What the hell's in Las Vegas?
美国证券化论坛下周将在那里召开
The American Securitization Forum is there next week.
每位债券和债务担保的交易员和次贷借贷者
Every bond and CDO salesman, subprime lender
以及掉期的交易员也会到场
and swap trader is gonna be there.
跟你们说  你们赌的就是那些傻瓜的钱
I'm telling you, your bet is against dumb money.
是时候让你们见识下什么叫人傻钱多
It's about time you find out just how dumb that money really is.
天  我讨厌拉斯维加斯
God, I hate Vegas.
听说那里的食物不错
I hear the food has gotten really good in Vegas.
现在也有一家松久日料餐厅了
They have a Nobu now.
你能不能消停会
Would you fucking stop it?
1月28日至31日  美国证券化论坛
拉斯维加斯
美国证券化论坛
汽车抵押贷款与工资日贷款
凯撒宫酒店
优选公司总裁保罗·丹托纳: 房贷市场十分稳健  日益壮大
有什么感觉吗
Any sense?
如果一个债券很贵  是什么意思
And if a bond is "Rich”, it is...
不知道  包含的资产很多吗
I don't know, loaded with assets?
贵的意思就是定价过高
"Rich" Just means overpriced.
我在飞机上睡不着  所以做了点准备
I can't sleep on planes, so I did my homework.
集中精神  咱们的目标是什么
Okay, let's focus. What's our goal?
来弄清楚这到底是千载难逢的机遇
To figure out if this is a deal of a lifetime
还是我们漏了什么不知道的细节
or if everyone here knows something we don't
然后亏得一文不剩
and we're gonna get royally screwed.
对  见到贝尔斯登公司的人时牢记这点
Right. Remember that when you meet with the guys from Bear.
我给你们安排了一次面谈
I set you up with a face-to-face.
-好棒  -在哪里
- Awesome. - Where is that?
天  五年前证券化论坛是个屌丝聚?
Holy shit. Five years ago, Securitization was a loser convention.
也就一两百人会到场
100, maybe 200 people would show.
规模达五千亿的一年后  变成现在这样
$500 billion a year later, you get this.
这里有不少爱装逼的人
There's a lot of smug-looking people in here, huh?
一个个暴发户
It's like someone hit a
装的像出身贵族似的
piniata filled with white people who suck at golf.
这些小丑都是什么来头
I mean, who are all these clowns?
-别这样  我觉得看着挺好玩  -闭嘴
- Oh, come on. I think it looks fun. - Shut up.
那肯定啊  温尼特说了
Certainly. Vennett says
咱们赚的可都是这些人的钱
these are the people we're betting against.
-咱们过去  走吧  -他在那
- Yeah, here we go. Here we go. - There he is.
克里斯走我左边  呆在我左边
Chris, on my left. Chris, on my left.
先生们
Gentlemen.
我们什么时候才有机会
When do we get a chance
与这里的人们面谈呢
to face time with some of these lovely folks?
克里斯  把门卡给他
Chris, give him the keycards.
你知道要给哪些门卡吗
Do you even know which keycards you're giving out?
-注意点别给错了  -谢谢
- You're just giving them out? - Thank you.
首先旅途如何  一切顺利吗
First of all, how was your travel? How are you? Uneventful?
-很顺利  -很好
- Uneventful. - Okay.
我到这六小时了  还去了健身房
I've been here for six hours. I've already been to the gym,
吃了两个水煮荷包蛋
I had two poached eggs
还和哈利·戴恩·斯坦通打了牌
and I played blackjack with Harry Dean Stanton.
谢谢你的日常报告
Thank you for your diary.
面谈  我想要面谈
Face time. I'd like some face time.
记住  我们来这是为了收集信息
Just remember. We're here to gather information.
我们是来获取情报的  好吗
We're gathering information, okay?
不是来大肆宣扬我们的立场  明白吗
We're not advertising our short position. All right?
我们不希望打草惊蛇  能做到吗
We don't want to spook everybody. Can you do that?
我知道你容易说漏嘴  还停不下来
I know you got a big mouth, you like to run it.
这几天能不能收敛下
Can you just keep it shut for a few days?
好吧  好吧
Okay. Okay.
别担心  我们会好好干的
Yeah, don't worry. We'll play nice.
女士们先生们
Ladies and gentlemen.
商业形势大好
Business is good.
利润丰厚
Profits are strong
而房贷还会继续成为
and the mortgage continues to be the bedrock
整个经济体系的中流砥柱
on which this economy is built.
是  去年我们不得不承担
And, yes, we had to take some losses
在次贷市场带来的损失  但是
in our subprime department last year, but those losses
损失将会被保持在5%以内
will be contained at only 5%.
现在  在住房地产业
Now, in our residential sector...
马克  还没到问答时间
Mark, it's not a Q and A.
我们推出的可调利率房贷产品
...our rollout of those variable rate packages
已被消费者一抢而空
were gobbled up by the consumers!
我有一个问题
I have a question, please.
先生  问答环节是在我讲话结束后
Sir, the Q and A is after my statements.
但看你很急的样子  请问吧
But you know what? You seem anxious. How can I help you?
-谢谢  你好吗  -很好  谢谢
- Thank you. How are you? - Fine, thank you.
你觉得次贷亏损
Would you say that it is a possibility
止步于5%的可能性有多大
or a probability that subprime losses stop at 5%?
谢谢
Thank you.
可能性非常大
I would say it is a very strong probability, indeed.
那么  回到房地产市场
So back to the residential sector.
我们推出新的浮动利率产品时
When we rolled out the new variable rates package...
打断一下
Excuse me.
请讲
Yes, sir.
零  零
Zero! Zero!
次贷亏损止于5%
There is a 0% chance
的可能性是零
that your subprime losses will stop at 5%.
零
Zero.
不好意思
Excuse me.
我得接个电话
I have to take this.
他肯定是美国银行的
He must be from Bank of America.
我们的次贷部门没事
Our subprime department is fine.
没  我现在什么也没干
No, I'm not doing anything right now.
就像我刚才说的  我们的房地产部门
As I was saying, our residential department...
孩子们怎么样
How are the kids?
消费者对我们产品的反应
...consumers reacted to our packages...
马克·鲍姆真的做到了
Mark Baum really did that.
我们在维加斯的时候  他做到了
When we were in Vegas, he did that.
他提问了  他还接了电话
He said that, he took the call.
现在你知道我对付他有多难了吧
Now you see what I had to deal with?
你那把贝瑞塔凑活吧
Yeah, the Beretta... Meh.
美国著名枪械制造买卖公司
我这把冲锋真他妈爽翻了
But this Uzi is fucking awesome!
一种以色列制冲锋枪
要是这债务担保生意能再持续两年
I need this CDO machine to run for another two years.
我就发大财了  就能在阿斯彭买房了
And then I'm rich as fuck and I got my house in Aspen.
科罗拉多中西部城市
但你担心这些基础资产证券化
But do you have any concerns about the performance
它们的风险吗
of the underlying securitizations?
拖欠和违约率
It's easy to see that delinquencies
现在明显在上涨
and default rates are on the rise right now.
你能不能别这么扫兴
Could you please stop being such a buzzkill, dude?
我们带你来这儿不是来讨论工作的
We didn't bring you out here to talk about work, bro.
那你带我们来干吗
Why did you bring us out here?
我们得把子弹钱从客户那儿挣回来
Because we need to be able to expense the ammo to a client.
我要去射恐怖分子了
I'm gonna go shoot some terrorists.
看我给你们来一手  小子们
Watch how it's done, boys!
两个白痴
These guys are morons.
这枪真他妈厉害
Fucking tool.
两个白痴
These guys are morons.
爽暴了
Fuck, yes! Boom!
我们要把这里所有
We need to be buying up
买得起的掉期都买下来
every swap we can get our hands on here.
等下  好吗  等下
Just hold on, okay? Hold on.
我哥的前女友在证券交易委员会工作
My brother's ex-girlfriend works for the SEC.
她刚才说她在这里
She just told me she's in town, okay?
我们如果漏了什么细节  她或许能告诉我
So, if we're missing something, maybe she can tell me.
给我点内部消息什么的
You know, give me some insight.
你也别闲着
In the meantime, you go to the main floor
去主楼打听下掉期的价格
and price some swaps.
其实  我们正打算投资一些房地产债券
Well, actually, we're about to invest in housing bonds, and...
我在想证交会对这块有没有什么担忧
I was wondering if the SEC is worried about them at all.
我知道你不能透露信息
I know you're not allowed
但给些方向也好
to tell me specifics, but just generally.
我们不调查房贷债券
Oh, we don't investigate mortgage bonds.
其实  因为预算缩减
Truth is, since we got our budget cut,
我们已经不怎么做调查了
we don't investigate much.
那你来这儿干吗
Then why are you here? I thought...
我不是来出差的
I'm not here for the SEC.
是因为有私事
I'm here on my own dime.
我在看能不能跳槽到某个大银行
I'm floating my resume to some big banks.
对了  你哥最近怎么样
How's your brother, by the way?
你怎么能跳槽到大银行呢
How are you floating your resume to big banks?
我是说  你本来应该是
I mean, you're supposed to be the ones,
监管大银行的
you know, policing the big banks.
别那么幼稚了  杰米
Grow up, Jamie.
肯定有什么法律规定
There must be some kind of
从金融监管机构离职后不能立即
law against working for a financial institution
到金融机构工作吧
right after you've been working in financial regulation, right?
没有  没有
No. No.
你好  道奇
Hey! Dougie!
你好  过来  你在这儿干吗
Hey! Come over here. What are you doing at Caesars?
他在高盛工作
He's at Goldman.
回见
See you.
或许我们可以在500基准点做BBB级掉期
We can do BBB-level swaps at 500 basis points. Maybe.
你给出的掉期价让人觉得  无论债券价值
You're pricing the swaps like the bond is gonna collapse
如何上涨  最终还是会暴跌  对吧
even though the bond value's going up? Really?
世事如此
Sign of the times.
到底怎么回事
What the hell is going on?
路易斯  你明天能早点来吗
Lewis, can you come in early tomorrow, please?
我得抛售美国国际集团  全美金融
I need to unload the AIG and Countrywide
美国国际集团  跨国保险及金融服务机构集团
全美金融  房屋抵押贷款机构
和房地美头寸
and Freddie Mac positions
美国房贷公司
这样我们才能有钱
so that we can afford the premiums on the...
交房贷空头掉期的溢价
...core mortgage shorts on the swaps.
没问题  柏利博士
No problem, Dr. Burry.
-柏利博士?  -怎么了
- Dr. Burry? - Hmm?
要是投资人撤资
If the investors withdraw,
结果会怎样  我们就完蛋了吗
what's going to happen here? Are we done?
说实话  我不知道
Honestly, I don't know.
债券不会下跌
The bonds aren't going down.
它们根本不会动  很可能
They won't move. It's possible
我们在一个完全做假的系统里
that we are in a completely fraudulent system.
或者  你判断错误
Or... You're wrong.
也是
Sure.
我也可能犯错  我只是不知道错在哪
It's possible I'm wrong. I just don't know how.
我猜犯错的人根本不
I guess when someone's wrong, they never...
他们根本不知道错在哪
They never know how.
明早见
See you in the morning.
Yeah.
连贝尔都提价了
Even Bear upped their prices.
他们还一直叫我们棕蛋[布朗菲尔德]
And they keep calling us Brownhole.
只是因为你们钱不够多  名不够响
You just don't have the money or the reputation.
别太当回事
Don't take it personally.
我今晚不想去脱衣舞俱乐部了
I don't think I have the strip club in me tonight.
我只要一杯姜汁汽水
I'm just gonna get some ginger ale
看些付费表演就好
and watch some pay-per-view.
我去订明早离开的机票
I'll book us some flights out for the morning.
我们需要一笔生意  对吗  生意
A deal. We need a deal, right? A deal.
一笔能我们担得起的生意
We need a deal we can afford.
一笔别人不会拒绝的生意
We need a deal that they're not gonna refuse.
那么  我们能怎么办  我们能
So... What can we do? We can...
AA级份额  我们赌AA级份额怎么样
The AA tranches. What if we bet against the AA tranches?
谁会拒绝这场赌局呢
Who's not gonna take that bet?
他们说其中95%是AAA级的
We know they say they're 95% AAA-rated,
可实际上大多只有25%
but in reality they're more like 25%.
有些根本就没有
Some of them are 0%!
而且如果低级份额超过8%就违约
We also know that if the bottom tranches fail at over 8%,
那高级份额就会受影响
the upper tranches are affected.
它们会变成零
They go to zero.
我敢打赌现在那些AA其实更像B
I'll bet you right now that those AA's are actually like B's.
当我没说后面这句话
I rarely ever say these words,
可我觉得查理是对的
but I think Charlie's right.
你看  本
Look, Ben.
收益是
The payoff
200比1
is 200 to 1.
但他们只看面值的评级
But they're all taking the ratings at face value.
所以他们对AA份额
So they're charging pennies
只会收很少的溢价
on the dollar a bet against the AA's.
你们和我想的一样天真
Just when I start thinking you guys are clowns...
世界上没人会赌AA级份额
No one on the planet's betting against AA's.
银行会以为我们不是喝大就是抽风了
The banks will think we're either high or having a stroke.
他们会收下我们交的每一分溢价
They'll take every dime we have to offer.
挺聪明
Kinda brilliant.
我们这可真是创举啊
This is what we did that no one else thought of.
连鲍姆和柏利都没想过做空AA
Not even Baum or Burry thought to short the AA's.
但我们想到了
But we did.
小小的棕蛋资本
Little Brownhole Capital.
我们有兴趣买空债务担保的AA份额
We're interested in shorting some of the AA tranche of CDOs.
不是吧  为什么
Come on, guys, what's the angle?
不为什么  我们是新手  有点兴奋
Oh, got no angle. We're new to this. We're just excited.
我们想做1500万美元的AA份额掉期
We want to do $15 million in swaps on the AA tranche.
我不明白
I don't understand.
你想买多少AA份额就买多少
You can buy as much AA tranche as you want.
4000万美元赌AA
$40 million against the AA.
兄弟  你要多少我卖多少
Brother, I will sell you as much as you want.
你懂我  鲍勃  成交吗
You understand perfectly, Bob. You want the deal?
行  我没问题
That's cool. That's all right with me.
荣幸之至
Pleasure.
别这样  停  停
Don't do that. Stop. Stop.
-别扭了  -查理
- Stop that. - Charlie.
别扭了  停
Stop it! Stop.
怎么了
What?
你们知道你们刚才做了什么吗
Do you have any idea what you just did?
当然  我们刚才做了这辈子最大的生意
Come on. We just made the deal of our lifetimes!
我们应该庆祝一下
We should celebrate.
你们刚才是在跟美国经济对赌
You just bet against the American economy.
没错  我们赌了
Fuck, yeah, we did!
也就是说
Which means...
也就是说要是我们对了
Which means if we're right...
要是我们对了  人们会无家可归
If we're right, people lose homes.
人们会失去工作
People lose jobs.
人们会失去退休存款
People lose retirement savings.
人们会失去养老金
People lose pensions.
你们知道我最讨厌银行业的是什么吗
You know what I hate about fucking banking?
它把人变成了数字  这里有个数字
It reduces people to numbers. Here's a number.
失业率每上升1%
Every 1% unemployment goes up,
就有4万人死亡  你知道吗
40,000 people die. Did you know that?
-不知道  -你知道吗
- No. - Did you know that?
不  我不知道
No, I didn't know that.
我们只是很兴奋
We were just excited.
别他妈再跳舞了
Just don't fucking dance.
-好吧  -你要去哪儿
- All right. - Where are you going?
刚才真是吓坏宝宝了
Whoa, I just got really scared.
首先  今天表现不错
First of all, great show today.
-你太出色了  -谢谢啊
- You were terrific. - Thank you.
你的大嘴就是关不牢啊
Your big mouth was a revelation.
谢谢你的夸奖
I appreciate that.
你担心你和你的掉期会被耍是吗
You worried you and your swaps are getting played?
这次你有机会
Well, this is an opportunity
认识你的赌局对手了
for you to meet who you're betting against.
尽量别太正义  听着点
Try not to get too righteous and listen a little.
好吧  这位是谁
Okay, fine. Who is this guy?
一个十足的混蛋
A real solid-gold asshole.
我是个债务担保经理
I'm a CDO manager.
债务担保经理
A "CDO manager"?
在哈丁顾问公司工作
Yeah, at Harding Advisors.
我不知道债务担保还要人管呢
I didn't realize that there was anything to manage with CDOs.
是吗
Oh.
我们选择加入债务担保组合的有价证券
We select the securities that go into the CDO portfolio
同时监控这些资产
and monitor the assets.
美林证券公司的债务担保多由我负责
I do most of Merrill Lynch's CDOs.
你代表投资人还是美林证券
Do you represent the investors or Merrill Lynch?
投资人
The investors.
是吗
You do.
-没错  -可是
- Yeah. - But...
你若不把美林证券的债券放进你的债务担保里
Merrill Lynch isn't gonna send you any customers
美林就不会给你任何客户
unless you put Merrill Lynch's bonds in your CDO.
好问题  我们这么说吧
Good question. Let's just say Merrill and I have, um...
我和美林关系不错
We have a good relationship.
你跟美林证券关系不错
You have a good relationship with Merrill Lynch.
我们合作很久了
We've been doing business together for a long time.
所以你发行的债务担保
And so the CDOs that you create
是质量最好价值最高的
are of the highest quality and the highest value.
-绝对的  -绝对的
- Absolutely. Yep. - Absolutely.
你们关心不断上升的信用违约率吗
Are you at all concerned about the rising default rates?
我相信这些产品没有风险  马克
I assume no risk for these products myself, Mark.
好
Okay.
我们再说直白一些  银行找你
So let me get this straight. The bank calls you up.
他们给你他们想卖的债券
They give you the bonds they want to sell.
他们给你客户
They give you clients,
他们给你钱经营你的生意
they give you money to run your business.
给你丰厚的报酬
Give you fat fees for doing so.
可你代表的是投资人
But you represent the investors?
是这样的吗
Is that right?
没错
Yeah.
可我们现在不在美林证券的大楼里
But we're not in the Merrill Lynch building.
-好  那你在哪儿  -我们在新泽西
- Okay. Where are you? - We're in New Jersey.
只有20分钟的距离
You're 20 minutes away.
要是坐直升机就只有5分钟
Well, five if you use a helicopter.
这很可笑吗
That's funny, huh?
可笑至极
That's hilarious.
天哪
Oh, boy.
你老板要炸了
Your boss is about to explode.
不  他好奇心太强  炸不了
No, he's too curious to explode.
等等  再说一遍
Hold on. Say that again.
债务担保A包含B的一部分
CDO "A" Has parts of CDO "B".
但是B又包含A的一部分
And CDO "B" Has parts of CDO "A".
而它们又被放进了C里
But then they both get put inside CDO "C".
对  那叫债务担保的平方
Yeah, that one's called CDO squared.
债务担保的担保
A CDO of a CDO.
明白吗
All right?
还有一种债务担保
And then there's CDOs made up of the opposite side
赌的是你和你掉期交易的输赢
of the bet you made with your swaps.
我们叫综合性债务担保
We call them synthetic CDOs.
你说什么  综合性债务担保
What did you say? Synthetic CDOs.
这太他妈疯狂了
That is fucking crazy.
不疯狂  相反  它超厉害
It's not. It's awesome.
他要怒了
His face is starting to boil.
他看起来像《沙丘》里的那个坏人
He looks like the bad guy from Dune.
根据弗兰克·赫伯特同名小说改编的科幻电影
好吧  假如
All right, let's say
你有一个次贷池  里面有5000万美元
you have a pool of $50 million in subprime loans.
你的综合债务担保和掉期交易
How much money could be out there betting on it,
押了多少钱在上面
in your synthetic CDOs and swaps
现在  就在今晚
right now, tonight?
我想想  5000万美元
Let's see, $50 million... Hmm...
1亿美元
A billion dollars.
什么
What?
要是迈克尔·柏利发现的
If the mortgage bonds that
房贷债券是火柴
Michael Burry discovered were the match...
担保房贷债券的市场
How much bigger is the market for insuring mortgage bonds
要比实际房贷大多少
than actual mortgages?
大约20倍
About 20 times.
要是房贷债券是火柴
If the mortgage bonds were the match
债务担保是吸饱煤油的抹布
and the CDOs were the kerosene-soaked rags,
综合性债务担保就是喝醉了的
then the synthetic CDO was the atomic bomb
总统手里握着的原子弹
with the drunk President holding his finger over the button.
就在那一刻  在那个失了声的饭馆
It was at that moment in that dumb restaurant
马克·鲍姆脸上一副痴呆的表情
with that stupid look on his face that Mark Baum realized
意识到整个世界的经济要崩溃了
that the whole world economy might collapse.
我知道你在想什么
And I know what you're thinking.
综合债务担保是个什么鬼玩意
"What the fuck is a synthetic CDO?"
让行为经济学之父理查德·泰勒博士
Well, here's Dr. Richard Thaler, father of behavioral economics
理查德·H·泰勒  博士
和赛琳娜·戈麦斯来给你解释
and Selena Gomez to explain.
赛琳娜·戈麦斯
国际歌星
好  综合债务担保原理是这样的
Okay. So here's how a synthetic CDO works.
假如我在一局21点中赌1000万美元
Let's say I bet $10 million on a blackjack hand.
1000万美元是因为这一局代表
$10 million because this hand is meant to represent
一个房贷债券
a single mortgage bond.
赛琳娜的这手牌很好  明牌18点
Okay, Selena has a pretty good hand here, showing 18.
庄家明牌是7点
Dealer showing seven.
赛琳娜这手牌真的很好
That's a really good hand for Selena.
胜算很大  实际上
Good odds. In fact,
她有87%的概率能赢这局
her chances of winning this hand are 87%.
因此  我的胜算很大  我连赢了好几局
So, my odds are good. I'm on a winning streak.
这里的每个人都跃跃欲试
Everybody in this place wants to get in on the action.
我怎么会输呢  对吗
How could I lose, right?
这就是个经典的错误
Now, this is a classic error.
在篮球中这叫热手谬误
In basketball it's called the Hot Hand Fallacy.
运动员连续投球命中
A player makes a bunch of shots in a row.
人们确信他们会投中下一个
People are sure they're gonna make the next one.
人们认为现在发生的一切
People think that whatever's happening now
将来还会继续发生
is gonna continue to happen into the future.
在房地产繁荣时期  市场持续火热
During the real estate boom, markets were going up and up
人们就认为房价再也不会下跌
and people thought they would never go down.
所以有些人边观察边想
So people who are watching and think that I won't lose
我不会输  然后开始下注
will make a side bet.
这是第一个综合债务担保
Now, this is the first synthetic CDO.
我爱赛琳娜·戈麦斯
I love Selena Gomez.
我出5000万美元赌她会赢
I bet you $50 million she wins.
我给你3比1的赔率
And I'll give you 3-to-1 odds.
3比1的赔率  我赌
3-to-1 odds? Okay, I'll take that bet.
现在  有其他人想赌
Now, somebody else is gonna want to make a bet
他们赌博的结果
on the outcome of their bet.
5000万赌她赢
Bet you 50 million she wins.
这就是综合债务担保2号
That will lead to synthetic CDO number two.
我出2亿跟你赌
Hey, I bet you $200 million that lady in the glasses
戴眼镜的女士会赢
wins that bet.
她可能会赢  所以我想要巨大的回报
She probably will win. So I want a great payoff.
20比1怎么样
How about 20-to-1?
成交
Deal.
这会一直继续  产生更多的综合性CDO
And this will go on and on with more and more synthetic CDOs.
我们可以把原始的1000万美元投资
And we can transform an original $10 million investment
变成几亿美元
into billions of dollars.
你没事吧
You okay?
没事
No.
我其实很恶心
I actually feel pretty sick.
我要走了
So I'm going to leave.
你觉得我是个寄生虫  是吧  鲍姆先生
You think I'm a parasite, don't you, Mr. Baum?
可是  社会显然觉得我很有价值
But, apparently, society values me very much.
事实上  我们来做笔交易
In fact, let's do this.
我会告诉你我值多少钱
I'll tell you how much I'm worth.
你告诉我你值多少钱
You tell me how much you're worth.
天哪  你就是一砣大狗屎
God, you are an incredibly big piece of shit.
那个人碰了什么就给我做空什么
Short everything that guy has touched.
再投五个亿进去
I want half a billion more in swaps.
你确定吗  抵押品会让你破产的
You sure about that? The collateral calls could bankrupt you.
我确定
Yeah. Yeah.
你要去哪里
Where are you going?
我要去轮盘桌上
I am going to try to find moral redemption
找道德救赎
at the roulette table.
事情比我想得要更糟
Things are worse than I thought.
我真的觉得经济会崩溃的
I honestly think the economy might collapse.
但你一直说
But you've been saying
这机制都已经崩坏好几年了  马克  所以
that the system's broken for years, Mark. So...
你有什么好惊讶的
Why are you so shocked?
因为它比我想象得更可怕
It's more twisted than I could have imagined.
你一直都喜欢做好人
You love to be the virtuous one.
我是个银行家  我是这之中的一部分
I'm a banker. I'm a part of it.
你一直都是  马克  但
You always have, Mark. Like
-出淤泥而不染  -它让我变成了一个
- you're untainted.  - It changed me. It changed me into a person
不会伸手去帮助别人的人
who is not able to reach out to someone...
他很痛苦  我的弟弟在受苦
He was in pain. My brother was in real pain.
本来就没什么好办法可以帮他
There's no perfect way to help.
是很悲伤  很吓人
It's sad. It's scary.
所以别再尝试拯救世界了
So stop trying to fix the world.
他告诉我
He told me...
你不是圣人
You're not a saint.
圣人是不会住在公园大道上的
Saints don't live on Park Avenue.
说他还有一些不好的想法
...that he was having bad thoughts.
就像普通人一样去感受自己就好了
Just feel the feelings like the rest of us.
我的第一反应是给他点钱
My first response was to offer him some money.
我他妈的给了他点钱
I offered him fucking money!
他的脸都摔烂了
His face was so smashed.
哭出来就好了
That's right.
迈克尔
Michael?
-迈克尔  -在的  我在
- Michael? - Yes. Yes.
-没事吧  -没事  亲爱的
- Is everything okay? - Yes, honey.
-你确定吗  -没事  宝贝
- You sure? - Yeah, baby.
我没事
I'm fine.
致投资者
To all investors.
如你们所知
As you may know,
我们的协议允许我在市场运行脱轨的情况下
our agreement allows me to take extraordinary measures
采取一些非常手段
when markets aren't functioning properly.
我现在有理由相信抵押债券市场
I currently have reason to believe the mortgage bond market
是存在欺诈的
is fraudulent.
所以为保护投资者们免遭虚假市场的伤害
So, in order to protect investors from this fraudulent market,
我决定要限制投资者撤资
I've decided to restrict investors' withdrawals
请等待更进一步的通知
until further notice.
迈克尔·J·柏利博士  敬上
Sincerely, Dr. Michael J. Burry.
其实每个人都在等待世界末日的来临
我从未想到过我的生活在搬到洛杉矶之后
I never would have guessed my life
会发生如此翻天覆地的变化
could change as much as it has since I moved to L.A.
不见你
It's not just,
不是那么容易做到的
like, that easy to, like, not see you.
他痛斥了那些说他使用了违禁药物的留言
He lashed out at rumors he used performance enhancing drugs.
这个记录是没有被污染过的
This record is not tainted.
天呐  兄弟
Oh, my God, dude.
能别再换台了吗
Will you please stop changing the channels?
-你快把我逼疯了  -好吧
- You're driving me crazy. - All right.
-好吧  -搁到经济频道就好
- Fine. - Just put the business news on.
标准普尔指数上升了3个点
...and the S&P picked up three points.
2007年4月2日
老天爷啊
Jesus!
房贷市场崩溃今天仍在继续
Mortgage meltdown continued today.
次贷出借人新世纪金融公司
Subprime mortgage lender New Century Financial,
昔日的行业领头人  申请了破产
once the industry leader, by the way, filed for bankruptcy.
该公司马上
The company immediately...
抵押贷款出借者破产
好的我们继续
Good time for my voice to go...
裁员了3200人
Fired 3,200 workers.
三月制造业指数也有所下跌
The manufacturing index also fell in the month of March...
开始了
It's starting.
专家提醒说经济增长趋势会放缓
...A warning that economic growth could slow.
供应管理学会
The Institute of Supply Management
也出台了价格上涨报告
also reported a rise in prices...
我要打给我妈
I'm gonna call my mom.
经济增长放缓的主要原因是
The principal source of the slowdown in economic growth...
一次又一次
Time and time and time again,
我都帮了你  马克
I have gone to bat for you, Mark!
我们已经认识七年了
We've known each other for seven years...
嗓门真大  真厉害
She's got some lungs on her. I'm impressed.
看她发火我还挺享受的
I can't help but enjoy it.
他妈没道理啊  他妈没道理
There's no fucking way. There's no fucking way
这些大银行都蠢成这样
that the big banks are that stupid.
再见  凯西
Bye, Kathy!
怎么样
Well?
凯西觉得我们做空
Kathy thinks that it would be a good idea
是个好主意
if we sold our shorts.
还有什么新闻不
What else is new?
她还说了摩根斯坦利投资公司会买
And she said that Morgan Stanley will buy them.
操
Holy shit!
你怎么说的
What did you say?
我跟她说我们什么也不卖
I told her we're not selling shit.
贝尔斯登在大量次贷损失后清算了两家对冲基金
如果你需要2005年的文件的话...
Uh, if you need the files for 2005...
菲尔德先生的诉讼尤其需要去年的资料
Mr. Fields' suit is very specific to files from the past year.
好  出去吧  替我跟劳伦斯说声好
Good. Then get out. Say hi to Lawrence for me.
好的
Will do.
你整整一周都不回复我
You can't call me back for a week?
真抱歉  迈克
I am so sorry, Mike.
高盛的系统崩溃了  我丢了好多消息
Goldman had a systems failure. I lost a ton of messages.
是吗  美国银行说他们有停电事故
Yeah, B of A said they had a power outage,
摩根斯坦利说他们的服务器挂了
and Morgan Stanley said their server crashed.
是挺奇怪的
Huh. That's weird.
我觉得那根本是不可能的
Well, I would call it improbable.
所以你把我们的定位定在哪里
So where do you have our position marked?
我觉得跟他们是一样的  迈克
I think it's the same, Mike.
什么  你能跟我解释一下吗
What? Can you explain that to me, please,
为什么投保的东西都转让了
because how can the value of an insurance contract
保险合同的价值却一点影响都不受呢
not be affected by the demise of the very thing it insures?
他们属于独立市场  并不是总是相关的
They're independent markets. They're not always correlated.
我知道这听起来很奇怪
I know it sounds odd,
但这本来就是非常复杂的产品
but these are very complicated products.
它们是互相关联的
They are correlated.
人们会失去房子  失去工作
They're gonna lose their houses, they're gonna lose their jobs,
会失去
they're gonna lose their...
你能不能好好听我说
Will you listen to me?
这就像是资本主义的末日
This is like the end of capitalism.
像是黑暗时期又回来了一样
This is like the Dark Ages all over again.
我不想跟爸爸说话
I don't want to talk to Dad.
好的  我也爱你  留着你的钱吧
Okay, I love you, too. Save your money.
她让我吃点赞安诺  左洛复剂量加倍
She says I need to be on Xanax and double my dose of Zoloft.
赞安诺  镇定剂
左洛复  抗抑郁药
我让贝尔斯登给我们的做空估个价
I asked Bear Stearns to price our shorts.
他们告诉我担保债务凭证的价格没变
They tell me the CDOs still haven't moved.
他妈真是疯了
This is fucking insane!
你意识到了吗
You realize that?
这些人都是骗子  他们都该进监狱
These people are crooks and they should be in prison.
看看次贷衍生债券综合指数
Look at the ABX.
你看这些担保债务凭证价格都成零了
You can see that the CDOs are worth zero!
你知道他们在干嘛
So you know what they're doing, huh?
你知道他们在干嘛  对吧
You know what they're doing, right?
是啊  他们在卸货
Yeah. They're unloading them.
他们先卖担保债务凭证  然后换家银行
They're selling their dog shit CDOs, then they go to another bank
把他们刚卖掉的东西做空
And short the shit they just fucking sold!
我们去找媒体吧  兄弟
Let's go to the press, man!
这么好的故事谁不想登啊
This is a massive story. Who wouldn't publish it?
罗伯特·雷德福德
Robert Redford!
不  你不懂
No, you don't understand!
我明白了  同志们  我明白了
I got it, guys. I got it.
美国1211大道[新闻大厦]
华尔街日报
我该怎么办呢
What am I supposed to do?
写篇文章  题目就叫《我们都玩完了》
Do you want me to write a piece called "We're All Fucked"?
好啊  简直完美
Yes! That's a perfect title!
凯西  现在大家都在卖这些垃圾债券
Casey, right now every bank in town is unloading these shit bonds
卖给不知情的客户
onto unsuspecting customers.
而且在卖出去之前他们是不会主动降价的
And they won't devalue them until they get them off their books.
这种程度的犯罪就算是在华尔街
This level of criminality is unprecedented,
也是前所未有的
even on fucking Wall Street.
杰米  我是说真的
Jamie... And this is me being honest here, okay?
我花了好几年才在华尔街有了这人脉
It took me years to build my relationships on Wall Street.
银行和评级机构不会确认这样的消息
No bank or ratings agency is going to confirm a story like this
就因为两个来自基金开在车库的家伙
just because it comes from two guys in a...
觉得世界末日要到了
Sorry, garage band hedge fund that thinks it's the apocalypse.
我以为你是有良心的  凯西
I thought you were for real, Casey.
我真的是这么想的
You know, I'll have to say I really did.
是吗
Really?
杰米  你要跟一个小孩才三岁
Yeah, Jamie, you try being for real with a three-year-old
老婆在读硕士的人谈良心
and a wife getting her master's degree.
我是不会为了你那点预感毁了我的名声的
I'm not gonna burn my reputation on your wild hunch.
多谢你们跑这一趟  兄弟
Thanks for coming, guys.
见到你们真是太好了
Totally fucking awesome to see you.
是啊  凯西  我一直对你很不爽来着
Yeah, Casey. I've always hated you,
因为你在大学里那臭屁样儿
because you were a prick in college
到今天也还是没变
and you are a prick today!
谢谢  查理  还跟你妈住一块儿呢
Thanks, Charlie. Still living with your mom?
查理  走
Charlie, come on!
我是马克·鲍姆  给我回电
Mark Baum again. Call me.
次级贷债券大跳水
Subprime bonds fell off a cliff.
传闻说有大批违约
Rumor has it the default numbers are huge.
是谁先拿到汇款数据的  我猜是高盛
Who got the remittance data early? I bet it's Goldman.
滚你的
Yeah, fuck you very much.
杰瑞德  这里真是一团糟  咱们什么情况
Jared, it's chaos down here. Where are we?
"凯撒哭了  因为再没有能征服的地方了"
"And Caesar wept, for there were no more worlds to conquer."
谢恩
Shane?
没人会买担保凭证和抵押债券了
Well, nobody's buying CDO or mortgage bonds anymore
人人都要掉期交易
and everybody wants swaps.
这现在是华尔街最抢手的东西了
Swaps are now the most popular product on the street.
-对我们是好事啊  -是  也不是
- That's good for us. - Yes and no.
我听人说  别人又听人说
I heard from somebody who heard from somebody...
不  亚历克斯  出去  抱歉
No, Alex, no. Sorry.
摩根的本尼·克里格
Bennie Cleager over at Morgan is taking on
在债券部门损失惨重
some heavy losses in the bond department.
发出全国范围内金融警告"困难时期"
你的船可能进水了
Your ship might be taking on water.
可能是时候穿上救生衣跑路了
It might be time to get our lifejacket and get out.
真是操蛋呀
I'm jacked.
真是操蛋啊
I'm jacked! I'm jacked to the tits!
好
Good.
-你感觉到了吗  -没有
- Do you feel it? - No.
你听到什么了  汤米
What'd you hear, Tommy?
开始了
It's happening.
大家都想要我们的掉期信贷
Everybody wants our swaps.
凯西找你
Kathy's office is looking for you.
他们又变卦了  是不是
They're singing a different tune now, aren't they?
情况不妙
That's not good.
等会再说  现在不行
Maybe later. Not now.
-这是开玩笑的吧  -绝对不要
- This is a joke. - Never.
我在听
Listening.
-柏利博士吗  -是的
-Dr. Burry? - Yeah.
我是高盛投资公司的狄·温斯顿
Deeb Winston, Goldman Sachs.
是这样  我看了下你给的价位
Listen, I've been reviewing your position.
想跟你讨论一下  确保它们是合理的
I wanted to discuss your marks and make sure they're fair.
那我想你们也已经
Yeah, I think you mean that you've
给自己留好了净空头仓位
secured a net short position yourselves.
这样你就可以随意给我的掉期信贷估价了
So you're free to mark my swaps accurately for once
因为现在已经任你宰割了
because it's now in your interest to do so.
我不知道你想让我说什么
I'm not sure what you want me to say.
我想
I think that...
我想你已经说出来了
I think that you've already said it.
你跟高盛的杰夫说我是不会转移基金的
You tell Jeff at Goldman that I'm not transferring funds.
真是胡扯
This is bullshit!
好的  我们等下再谈
Okay, we'll talk later.
谢谢你
Thank you.
谢谢你来的这么快  马克
Thanks for coming so quickly, Mark.
我知道你最近听到了
I know you've been hearing rumblings
摩根受损的一些消息
about some losses Morgan has suffered.
-祝贺你  -祝什么
- Congratulations. - On what?
谢谢
Thanks.
玩的开心吗
Having fun?
不错
Yes.
非常好
Tons.
我只是想跟你说
I just wanted you to know that, um...
的确  摩根的确有所损失
that, yes, Morgan has suffered some losses,
但我们的流动资金相当充足  不必担心
but our liquidity is strong and there's no cause for concern.
本尼·克里格会担心吗
Would Bennie Cleager be concerned?
因为传闻说
Because word on the street
他的损失也不小
is that he took some pretty heavy losses.
凯西  拜托  我们已经很熟了
Kathy, come on. We know each other.
发生什么事了
What's going on?
情况有多糟
How bad is this?
好吧
Okay.
两年前  本尼·克里格在摩根的债券部门
Two years ago, Bennie Cleager in Morgan's bond department
也在做空次级房贷  二十亿做空3B级公司
also started shorting subprime housing, $2 billion in BBBs.
本尼比我想的要聪明
Bennie is smarter than I thought.
不  一点都不聪明
No, he's not smart at all.
掉期信贷的溢价吃掉了他的利润
The premiums on the swap ate into his desk's profit.
为了掩饰他在BBB的做空
To cover his BBB shorts,
他卖了很多A级和AA级掉期来自保
he sold a lot of A and AA swaps as protection.
非常多
A lot.
他相信它们是不会被影响到的
He believed that there was no way that they could be affected.
告诉我摩根斯坦利没有这些互换信贷的合同
Tell me Morgan Stanley doesn't hold the contracts on these swaps.
操
Holy shit.
这段时间我一直都
All this time I've been
在想我到底在跟谁赌
trying to figure out who I'm betting against,
没想到是摩根斯坦利
and it's Morgan Stanley.
也就是我自己
Which is me.
风险敞口是多少  三十亿吗
What's your exposure? $3 billion?
拜托  别跟我说超过四十亿了
Please, don't tell me it's more than four.
我不能回答  我不能回答你
I can't answer that. I can't answer that.
可以的  你说的出的  因为我走进这里
Yes, you can answer that, because I walk in here
看到你手下的人都在走廊里哭天喊地的
and people are crying in your hallway.
凯西
Kathy,
你把我带进来然后告诉我没事的
you bring me in to tell me everything's fine,
但根本不是这样
and everything's not fine.
到底  发生什么事了
What, what is happening?
多头敞口是
The long exposure is...
150亿
...$15 billion.
老天爷啊
Jesus!
他一直说违约金不可能超过8%的
He kept saying defaults over 8% were impossible.
我的天呐
Oh, my God.
还说会有100万人无家可归呢
That there would be a million homeless!
是啊  但我们跟摩根斯坦利可没关系
Yeah, but we have nothing to do with Morgan Stanley.
告诉破产法院
Tell the bankruptcy court.
如果摩根破产  我们的钱就都归他们了
Morgan fails, all our accounts go on their balance sheet.
真是疯了
It's just crazy.
摩根自己打的烂赌
Morgan makes the sucker's bet
要我们替他还赌债
and we pay their fucking gambling debt?
做空银行股  然后等
Short the bank stocks. Then we wait.
或者等市场开  卖掉我们的掉期信贷
Or we sell our swaps when the market opens.
我们拿奖金  投资人拿收益
We get our bonuses, our investors get their profits, we get...
我们能拿到30%  凑活了
What, 30 cents on the dollar? It's not bad.
我们值三倍好嘛
We're three times that.
但如果没有市场卖就不一定了
Not if there's no market left to sell them in.
别管了  我们是不会去救他们的
Forget it. We're not giving out any lifeboats.
如果摩根沉了  我们就什么都没了
If Morgan goes under, we end up with nothing.
维尼
Vinnie.
天呐  拜托  要我说就卖掉
Jesus, come on. I say when we sell.
我知道这对你来说还有私人原因在
Look, I get that this is personal for you,
但我们有信托责任
but we have a fiduciary responsibility.
不  不  我们没有
No. No, we don't.
反正也没人负责
Nobody's acting responsible.
去他妈的责任  你是在逗我吗
Fuck responsibility. Are you kidding me?
让那些大银行的混蛋去负吧
The assholes at the big banks will take...
你们有什么想吃的吗
You boys want any appetizers?
我们有事谈
We're talking, please!
-不用管我们  -抱歉
- Excuse us. - Sorry.
我们等  然后等
We are going to wait, and we are going to wait,
一直等
and we are going to wait
等到他们感受到痛  等到他们开始流血
until they feel the pain, until they start to bleed.
-这就是我想要的  -但我们的客户怎么办
- That is what I want. - But what about our clients
他们把积蓄都托付给我们了
who've entrusted us with their savings...
我说我们卖掉的时候
I say when we sell.
这不是在说你
This isn't about you.
也不是说你和你上东区的
This isn't about you and your Upper East Side
-红木皂盒  -注意点
- mahogany soapbox. - Hey! Hey!
我说我们卖掉
I say when we sell!
你说了算  马克
Whatever you say, Mark.
兄弟  你看新闻了吗
Dude, did you hear the news?
好吧  所以不光是贝尔斯登的
Okay. So, not only do two mortgage hedge funds
两个的抵押债券对冲垮了
backed by Bear Stearns go belly up,
现在还针对贝尔来了一场集体诉讼
but now there's a class-action lawsuit against Bear.
操
Holy shit!
加油  踩  踩
Let's go! Push! Push!
所以呢  贝尔可能就真的完蛋了
So, what? Bear could really collapse here.
-我们真的不该冒这个险  -所以呢
- This is a risk we really shouldn't take. - Then what?
我们80%的掉期在贝尔买的
We bought 80% of our swaps at Bear.
-我们会损失一切  -所以呢
- We'd lose everything. - So what?
-先生  -稍等
- Hey, sir? - One second!
这是我的观点
That's my opinion.
我们买了这鬼东西
We bought these fucking things.
完全不知道怎么卖掉它们
We have no clue how to sell them.
我知道  我们必须要找本来卖
I know. We have to get Ben to do it.
我试过联系他  但他不会回电的
I've been trying to call him and he won't get back to me.
不  他和他老婆一家在度假
No. He's on vacation with his wife's family.
他们在英国
They're in England.
什么
What?
埃克斯茅斯  英格兰
黑马酒馆
太早说这个了
查理  所以
本  放轻松
查理  你电话坏了吗
杰米  我很平静  查理倒下了
本  美银不要
本  大摩还没回
杰米  操
本  太早说这个了
-本  你好啊  -小伙子们
- Hello, Ben. Hey. - Guys?
我们在呢  你听得到吗
Yeah, we're here. Can you hear us?
-小伙子们  -我们听到你了
- Guys? - Yeah, we got you.
我这里几乎没有信号  也没无线
Yeah. I hardly got cell phone or Wi-Fi service.
我要努力卖2亿证券
I'm trying to sell $200 million worth of securities.
在一个酒馆里  味道像羊
In a pub. It smells like sheep.
你能做到的
You can do this.
我不想催你  本
I don't want to pressure you, Ben
但你要是不答应的话  我们就全亏了
but if you don't pull this off, we lose everything.
好吧  我去问问看瑞信有没有兴趣
All right. Let's see what Credit Suisse's appetite is.
这里是棕地基金
This is Brownfield Fund.
我想卖一些信用掉期互换
I want to unload my credit default swaps.
好吧  你有什么
All right. What you got?
20个AA级资产支持证券的担保凭证
Twenty AA tranches of A.B.S. CDOs.
资产支持证券  这些有很差吗
A.B.S.? Are these... These are pretty bad?
非常差  屎一样
Absolutely. They're complete shit.
多少面值的
What's your notional value?
2亿5百万  美金
Face value is 205 million. Dollars.
好吧  40
All right, we could, we could go to forty.
不行  至少1个亿
No. We want at least 100 million.
1个亿  你是谁啊  毒枭还是银行家
100 million? Who are you, a drug dealer or a banker?
你要是银行家  就给我滚出去
'Cause if you're a banker, you can fuck right off!
我们不知道能不能做市
I don't know if we can make a market.
你最高能给多少
Just give me your best price?
给1个亿给我啦
Yeah. Chuck 100 million in for me, mate.
我们离太远了
I think we're far apart.
你要是不想做我们就不多说了
Look, if you don't want the deal, you can just hang up.
我是这么想的
That's what I thought.
-9千万  -7千
- 90 million. - 70.
8千5
85.
-7千8  -8千4
- 78. - 84.
这里是柏利博士
It's Dr. Burry.
看来金融业的崩溃已经来了
Looks like the collapse of the financial sector is imminent.
全国违约率超过12%
我们开始卖持仓
Let's start to sell my position.
总共13亿
It's $1.3 billion.
行  我等着
Sure, I'll hold.
亲爱的劳伦斯
您在赛恩资本盈利共4亿8千9百万已存入您账户
不用谢
我是对的
So, I was right.
我拿屎拿了两年
I took a rash of shit for two years, but
但我是对的
I was right.
所有人都错了
And everyone was wrong.
对  我为此拿了奖金  告我吧
And, yeah, I got a bonus check for it. Sue me.
你知道吗
You know?
这是很大一笔钱  我懂
It's a lot of money. I get it.
我能感觉到你在批判我
I can feel you judging me.
显而易见
That's palpable.
但我从没说我是这个故事的英雄
But, hey, I never said I was the hero of this story.
本  怎么样了
Hey, Ben. How are we looking?
8...万
Eight... on...
什么
Sorry?
不是  8千万
No. Eighty million.
8千万  8千万  不错  对不对
$80 million, $80 million, that's good, right?
-8千很好  -对不对
- Eighty is great. - Is that good?
-8千很好  本  -好吧
- Eighty is great, Ben. - Okay.
谢谢  非常感谢
Thank you. Thank you so much.
大部分给瑞银了
Most of it went to UBS.
你们很幸运  法国最大的银行
You're very lucky. The largest bank in France
今天冻结了客户的货币市场账户
froze customer's money market accounts today.
这事影响已经波及欧洲
This thing's hitting Europe.
希腊和爱尔兰完蛋了
Greece and Iceland are finished.
西班牙岌岌可危
Spain is teetering.
你是认真的吗  操
Are you serious? Fuck.
本  回来给我们电话
Ben, call us when you get home.
听着  挂之前
But, hey, before you go,
我想问
uh, I'm just wondering...
那个
Um...
你为什么帮我们一起
Why did you do this with us?
你没必要的
You didn't have to. Uh...
谢谢  不过  为什么
Thank you. But, uh, why?
你们说想变有钱  现在你们有钱了
You guys said you wanted to get rich. Now you're rich.
进球
Goal!
潘普洛纳将自己送上了记分牌
Pamplona puts themselves on the scoreboard.
3月14日  2008年
房地产市场与银行继续大出血
As the housing markets and banks continued to hemorrhage,
只有一个大空头拒绝
only one of the big shorts refused to sell.
马克·鲍姆
Mark Baum.
他在一次会议中被邀请与对手
So it was beyond perfect when he was asked to speak
著名的多头布鲁斯·米勒对峙
at a conference opposite Bruce Miller,
实在太完美了
the famous bullish investor.
他和马克辩论以后  格林斯潘
After he and Mark had their debate, Alan Greenspan,
整个危机的铸造者之一也会讲话
one of the architects of the whole crisis was scheduled to speak.
马克办公室的每个人都到场了
Everyone in Mark's office showed up,
他甚至还邀请了朋友
he even invited friends.
这是金融界的阿里大战福尔曼
This was the Ali vs. Foreman of the financial world.
现实主义大战傻瓜
The realist versus the fools.
如果这听上去太完美了  相信我  这是真的
And if it seems almost too perfect, trust me, this happened.
欢迎大家  有请
Welcome, everyone. Please give a generous welcome to
布鲁斯·米勒先生和马克·鲍姆先生
Mr. Bruce Miller and Mark Baum.
系好安全带
Strap yourself in.
有些人或许已经知道  贝尔斯通
So as some of you may know, Bear Stearns
刚收到摩根大通的贷款
has just received a loan from JP Morgan.
当然我们要等待观察
Of course, we're gonna have to wait and see
市场的反应
how the markets react,
但这应该解决了关于银行状况的担忧
but that should lay to rest any concerns about the bank's health.
我的理解是你不准备
Now, I take it you have no plans
卖掉你手中2亿的贝尔股票
to sell your $200 million in Bear stock?
不  实际上  我们这里结束了
No. As a matter of fact, when we're done here,
我可能还会去多买一点
I'll probably go out and buy some more.
反面观点  鲍姆先生
For the opposing view, Mr. Baum.
我要站起来说
I got to stand for this.
好吧  你们好
Okay, hi.
我司的观点很简单
My firm's thesis is pretty simple.
华尔街把一个好主意  路易斯·拉涅利的房贷债券
Wall Street took a good idea, Lewis Ranieri's mortgage bond,
变成了一颗
and turned it into an atomic bomb
骗局与愚蠢交织的原子弹
of fraud and stupidity
并且正要炸毁世界经济
that's on its way to decimating the world economy.
你怎么感觉到的
How do you really feel?
很高兴你还能开玩笑
I'm glad you still have a sense of humor.
如果我是你就不会这样
I wouldn't if I were you.
任何认识我的人都知道
Now, anyone who knows me knows that
我对别人的的错误直言不讳
I have no problem telling someone they're wrong.
贝尔斯登否认流动性问题的传闻
Bear Stearns is denying rumors of liquidity problems.
贝尔39
贝尔47
贝尔41
天哪  39了
Holy fuck, it's 39 now!
美国生活在一个诈骗时代
We live in an era of fraud in America.
不仅在银行业  也在政府
Not just in banking, but in government,
教育  宗教  食品
education, religion, food,
甚至棒球
even baseball.
困扰我的并不是
What bothers me isn't that
欺诈不好或者欺诈很坏
fraud is not nice or that fraud is mean.
而是150世纪以来
It's that for 15,000 years
行骗和短视
fraud and short-sighted thinking
从来没有成功过
have never, ever worked.
天哪  贝尔37了  -没有一次
- Jesus, Bear at 37... - Not once.
最终  人被抓  事变糟
Eventually, people get caught, things go south.
直线下跌
It's fucking plummeting, man.
我们什么时候忘记这些的
When the hell did we forget all that?
我以为我们更聪明  我真这么以为
I thought we were better than this. I really did.
发现这个事实
And the fact that we're not
并没让我感到轻松或是优越
doesn't make me feel all right and superior.
我觉得  悲伤
It makes me feel... Sad.
我每刷新一下就看到新低
Every time I fucking hit "Refresh" It's dropping, man.
贝尔35
看着虚华愚笨的
And as fun as it is to watch
华尔街犯错  赏心悦目
pompous, dumb Wall Streeters be wildly wrong,
你的确错了  先生
and you are wrong, sir,
我知道  事情的最后
I just know, that at the end of the day
付出代价的
average people are going to be the ones
却是普通民众
that are gonna have to pay for all this.
永远只是民众
Because they always, always do.
32了
It's 32.
沉底了
It's fucking tanked, man.
这是我要说的  谢谢
That's my two cents. Thank you.
我去恶心一下德银
Let me drop a deuce at Deutsche.
我们的多头有反击吗
Does our bull have a response?
我只能说  华尔街的历史上
Only that, in the entire history of Wall Street,
从未有投资银行倒下
no investment bank has ever failed
除非那个银行犯了罪
unless caught in criminal activities.
对  我坚持贝尔斯通的乐观
So, yes, I stand by my Bear Stearns optimism.
米勒先生  对不起  很快地问个问题
Mr. Miller, I'm sorry. Quick question.
从你们开始发言
From the time you guys started talking,
贝尔斯通的股票已经跌了38%
Bear Stearns stock has fallen more than 38%.
你还会买更多吗
Would you still buy more?
对  我当然会买  为什么不呢
Yeah, sure, of course I'd buy more. Why not?
嘭
Boom.
天哪
Jesus Christ!
第一部分称述就结束了
That concludes the first part of our presentation.
下一部分  我们邀请到著名的美联储前主席
Up next, we have the legendary former chairman of the Fed,
艾伦·格林斯潘
Alan Greenspan.
大家
Folks?
贝尔斯通首先倒下  影响全国  现在雷曼兄弟
雷曼兄弟的雇员们今天离开
...employees of Lehman Brothers today,
这家华尔街巨头的股价已跌至0
as the Wall Street giant's stock went to zero.
这家可敬的纽约银行破产
The collapse of the venerable New York bank
源于几个月以来的市场动荡
follows a tumultuous few months of market volatility
以及对世界经济的担忧
and fear in the world economy.
我一定要进去看看
I got to see inside.
怎么进去
How?
过来
Come on.
我把手机丢办公室了  也已经扔了通行证
I left my phone in the office. I threw my pass out already.
不介意我借你的用一下吧
Do you mind if I take your pass?
我不在乎这个了  随便你
I don't give a shit anymore. You can do what you want.
直接走去你的交通工具
Go directly to your transportation.
不要和媒体说话
Do not talk to the press.
18年了  我就这么走了  真他妈的棒
After 18 years, I just leave? That's just fucking great!
我爱和谁说和谁说
I'll talk to whoever the hell I want!
不要和媒体说话
Do not talk to the press.
直接前去交通工具
Go directly to your transportation.
不要和
Do not talk to...
你要一起吃饭吗
Hey, look, you wanna get a bite tonight?
有个新的古巴饭店
There's this, uh, new Cuban place
下东区刚开张的  应该很不错
just opened on the Lower East Side. It's supposed to be good.
-真的吗  -对
- Oh, really? - Yeah.
你和我
You and I?
对  再叫别人也行
Yeah, or other people.
-听上去不错  我想去  -好
- That sounds nice. I would like that. - Yeah.
重要
Finally.
马克
Mark, hey.
这里是一场血战
It's a bloodbath up here.
摩根股票已经折半了
Morgan stock has lost half its value.
现价23.1  直线跌落
It's down to 23. 10. It's in freefall.
客户想和你商量赎回
Clients want to talk to you about pulling their money.
现在不卖就没机会了  马克  我们必须卖
It's now or never, Mark. We got to sell.
马克
Mark.
马克  你听见我说话了吗
Mark, you hear me?
语音信箱1
Mailbox one.
你收到15条信息
You have 15 messages.
麦克  我没法联系到你
Mike, I can't seem to get ahold of you.
能否有空马上回电
Will you please call me at your earliest convenience.
这是杰克  你想买股票吗
It's Jack. You're buying stocks?
市场在历史地点  简直疯了
The market's at an all-time low. This is crazy!
我是在真爱网认识我妻子的
I met my wife on Match.Com.
我的档案说
My profile said,
我是一个医学生  只有一只眼睛
"I am a medical student with only one eye,
我有社交障碍
"An awkward social manner,
我还有14.5万学生贷款
"And $145,000 in student loans."
她回信道
She wrote back,
你就是我要找的人
"You're just what I've been looking for."
她说的是诚实
She meant honest.
那我实话实说
So let me be honest.
房地产危机
The housing crisis represents
代表着最大的投资机会
the greatest financial opportunity of...
赚钱不是我想象那样
Making money is not like I thought it would be.
这生意扼杀了人性重要的一部分
This business kills the part of life that is essential.
和生意完全无关的一部分
The part that has nothing to do with business.
过去的两年  我的内心
For the past two years, my insides...
倍感吞噬
...have felt like they're eating themselves.
所有我尊敬的人
All the people I respected
都不再和我交谈
won't talk to me anymore
除非律师传话
except through lawyers.
人们
- - People
向权威求教如何定价
want an authority to tell them how to value things...
但他们不是通过事实与结果来甄选权威
...but they choose this authority not based on facts or results.
而是根据表象与耳熟程度
They choose it because it seems authoritative and familiar.
我是无论如何
And I am not
不可能变得亲切熟悉的
and never have been "Familiar".
因此
So...
我忧郁地发现
So, I've come to the sullen realization
我必须关闭基金
that I must close down the fund.
真诚的  迈克尔·J·柏利  医学博士
Sincerely, Michael J. Burry, M.D.
我想象的不是这样
This isn't how I pictured it.
你以为我嘛会见到什么
What did you think we'd find?
不知道
I don't know.
成年人
Grownups.
马克  你在吗
Mark, you there?
马克
Mark?
保尔森和伯南克刚从白宫出来
Paulson and Bernanke just left the White House.
将有纾困
There's going to be a bailout.
他们没别的选  不是吗
Well, they had to. Right?
不然就全完了
Paper markets would've collapsed.
他们早知道
They knew.
取款机里出不了现钞
Cash would've stopped coming out of ATMs.
他们必须支持
They had to backstop this.
他们早知道纳税人会买单
They knew the taxpayers would bail them out.
他们不是犯傻  他们只是不在意
They weren't being stupid. They just didn't care.
对  他们是该死的骗子嘛
Yeah. 'Cause they're fucking crooks.
起码有人会因此进监狱
But at least we're going to see some of them go to jail.
对吗  我说  他们必须拆分银行
Right? I mean, they're gonna have to break up the banks.
我说  狂欢结束了
I mean, the party's over.
我不知道  不知道  维尼
I don't know. I don't know, Vinnie.
我感觉
I have a feeling
几年后人们
that in a few years people are gonna be doing
就会像经济不好时都做的那样
what they always do when the economy tanks.
归咎与移民与贫民
They will be blaming immigrants and poor people.
但马克错了
But Mark was wrong.
接下去几年  成百上千的银行家
In the years that followed, hundreds of bankers
和评级机构坐了牢
and rating agencies executives went to jail.
证监会接受了彻底检查
The SEC was completely overhauled.
国会被迫拆分大银行
And Congress had no choice but to break up the big banks
并规范贷款与衍生品市场
and regulate the mortgage and derivatives industries.
开玩笑的
Just kidding.
银行拿着美国人民给的钱
The banks took the money the American people gave them
用来支付自己的年终奖
and used it to pay themselves huge bonuses
游说国会掐死大改革
and lobby Congress to kill big reform.
然后他们指责移民和贫民
And then they blamed immigrants and poor people.
这回  他们还指责教师
And this time, even teachers.
一切尘埃落定之后
And when all was said and done,
只有一个银行家进了监狱
only one single banker went to jail.
这个可怜的家伙
This poor schmuck.
瑞信的卡里姆·塞拉盖尔丁
Kareem Serageldin from Credit Suisse.
他隐瞒了几十个亿的贷款债券损失
He hid a few billion in mortgage bond losses,
危机中大部分大银行
something most of the big banks
都这么做
did on a good day during the crisis.
马克  我们可以卖了么
Mark, can we sell now?
基金会赚奖金10个亿
The fund will make almost $1 billion.
你能拿到2000万  马克
You'll clear $200 mil, Mark.
你知道  我们一旦卖了
You know, once we sell,
我们就和其他人一样了
we'll be just like the rest of them.
你知道
You know that.
我们不一样  我们不是那些坏人
No, we're not. We're not the bad guys here.
我们没有欺骗美国人民
We didn't defraud the American people and prey on their dreams
并且利用他们想成家的方法牟利
prey on their dreams of owning a home. All right?
是他们做的
They did.
我们现在狠狠地打了他们一拳
And now we get to kick them in the teeth.
10亿美金
A billion dollars.
对
That's right.
但我们必须现在清仓  不然就是零
But we got to close out our position or it could be zero.
马克  现在不清就来不及了
I mean, it's now or never, Mark.
好吧
Okay.
全卖掉
Sell it all.
尘埃落定  5万亿养老金  地产价值
40.1万存款和债券人间蒸发
仅在美国  800万人失去工作  600万人失去住房
马克·鲍姆的妻子  辛西娅
说马克在崩盘后其实很宽厚  从不对任何人说  我早说了这样
丹尼  维尼和波特仍在曼哈顿管理一个基金
那里有家松久日料餐厅
查理·盖乐和杰米·希普利试过告评级机构
被所有法律部门嘲笑
杰米仍然管理棕地但查理离开纽约  和夏洛特开始了一个家庭
本·瑞科特和妻子住在大果园里
他们有许多种子
迈克尔·柏利联系政府许多次  想知道是否有人有兴趣采访自己  从而知道自己如何最早预见整个系统的崩溃
没人回他电话  但他被联调局审计盘问了四次
他现在只做一个商品的投资:
水
2015年  几大银行开始卖几十亿定制分级机会
彭博新闻报道  这不过是信用担保凭证的另一种说法